<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://esteemed.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://esteemed.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-12-14T12:29:52+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Esteemed.io</title><subtitle>Best-in-class, Esteemed is the fastest-growing AI-powered talent management and career solutions provider delivering frictionless hiring and talent incubation for digital professionals.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">How to Hire a Coder: The Ultimate Guide for Success</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2024/07/16/how-to-hire-a-coder/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Hire a Coder: The Ultimate Guide for Success" /><published>2024-07-16T18:42:39+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-16T18:42:39+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2024/07/16/how-to-hire-a-coder</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2024/07/16/how-to-hire-a-coder/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-ultimate-guide-how-to-hire-a-coder-for-your-next-project">The Ultimate Guide: How to Hire a Coder for Your Next Project</h1>

<p>Whether you need a website, an app, or software, finding and hiring a coder is essential for bringing your project to life. A recent survey showed that <a href="https://techved.medium.com/from-talent-shortage-to-talent-abundance-how-team-augmentation-helps-492c6d4f934a">83% of tech leaders struggle to find qualified tech talent</a>; it’s crucial to know how to navigate the hiring process effectively.</p>

<h3 id="importance-of-hiring-a-skilled-coder">Importance of Hiring a Skilled Coder</h3>

<p>A skilled coder is vital for the success of your project. They ensure your project runs smoothly, functions well, and provides a great user experience. Moreover, a competent coder can give you a competitive edge, streamline operations, and open up new growth and partnership opportunities.</p>

<h3 id="understanding-your-project-requirements">Understanding Your Project Requirements</h3>

<p>Before starting your search, clearly define your project’s goals, features, and technologies. Doing so will help you to identify the specific skills and expertise required, ensuring you hire the right person. Consider the project timeline and budget to set realistic expectations and guide your search.</p>

<h3 id="types-of-coders-and-their-specialties">Types of Coders and Their Specialties</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Front-End Developers</strong>: Focus on the visual and interactive parts of a website or app using HTML, CSS, and JavaScript. They create the user interface and the user experience.</li>
  <li><strong>Back-End Developers</strong>: Handle server-side logic, databases, and APIs using languages like Python, Ruby, Java, or PHP. They ensure the application functions properly and efficiently.</li>
  <li><strong>Full-Stack Developers</strong>: Work on both front-end and back-end parts of a project, integrating the two . They are versatile and can manage the entire development process.</li>
  <li><strong>Mobile App Developers</strong>: Specialize in creating apps for iOS and Android platforms using Swift, Objective-C, Kotlin, or Java. They focus on delivering high-performing mobile experiences.</li>
  <li><strong>Data Scientists and Engineers</strong>: Experts in data analysis, building data pipelines, and developing predictive models with Python, R, or SQL. They transform data into actionable insights.</li>
</ul>

<p>Understanding these specialties can help you align your project needs with the right talent.</p>

<h3 id="where-to-find-coders-for-hire">Where to Find Coders for Hire</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Online Freelance Marketplaces</strong>: Platforms like <a href="https://colleagues.esteemed.io/talent">Colleagues</a> offer a vast pool of freelance coders.</li>
  <li><strong>Specialized Coding Job Boards</strong>: Websites like GitHub Jobs, Stack Overflow Jobs, and AngelList are great places to find skilled coders.</li>
  <li><strong>Referrals and Professional Networks</strong>: Talk with industry contacts for recommendations.</li>
  <li><strong>Coding Communities and Forums</strong>: Engage with online communities like Hacker News, and local tech meetups.</li>
  <li><strong>Staffing Agencies and Recruitment Firms</strong>: Consider working with specialized tech staffing agencies for a streamlined hiring process.</li>
</ul>

<p>For more tips on where to find coders, visit <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/the-beginners-guide-to-screening-and-evaluating-tech-candidates/">this guide on screening and evaluating tech candidates</a>.</p>

<h3 id="evaluating-coder-portfolios-and-resumes">Evaluating Coder Portfolios and Resumes</h3>

<p>Review coder portfolios and resumes to assess their skills and experience. Look at their past projects, the technologies they’ve used, and the quality of their work. Ensure they have relevant experience and good communication skills. For more detailed advice, read this <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/09/29/why-fractional-screening-is-a-great-side-hustle-for-developers/">guide on how developers screen one another</a>.</p>

<h3 id="conducting-technical-interviews">Conducting Technical Interviews</h3>

<p>Technical interviews are crucial for evaluating a coder’s abilities. Ask questions related to the programming languages and tools your project requires. Present coding challenges to see how they approach problem-solving and write code. This <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/technical-screening-in-2022-15-methods-for-assessing-senior-and-junior-developers/">guide on technical screening</a> provides more insights.</p>

<h3 id="assessing-coding-skills-and-problem-solving-abilities">Assessing Coding Skills and Problem-Solving Abilities</h3>

<p>Consider coding tests or challenges that align with your project requirements. Look at their code samples on platforms like GitHub. Assess their ability to work with your tech stack and their enthusiasm for learning new tools. Learn more about <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Mbal1cYFx3s">assessing coding skills</a>.</p>

<h3 id="negotiating-rates-and-contracts">Negotiating Rates and Contracts</h3>

<p>Research industry rates to make a fair offer. Discuss terms like payment schedules, ownership rights, confidentiality, and project deliverables. Ensure the contract protects both parties’ interests.</p>

<h3 id="onboarding-and-managing-coders">Onboarding and Managing Coders</h3>

<p>Provide a clear onboarding process and set communication expectations. Use project management tools to track progress. Regular check-ins and feedback sessions are essential for keeping the project on track.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion-and-final-tips-for-hiring-a-coder">Conclusion and Final Tips for Hiring a Coder</h3>

<p>Clearly define your project requirements, understand the types of coders, and thoroughly evaluate candidates. Invest time in technical interviews and negotiating fair contracts. Effective onboarding and communication are key to a successful project. The right coder can transform your idea into a successful reality.</p>

<p>Remember, the right coder can be a game-changer for your project, so take the time to find the perfect fit. With this guide, you’re well on your way to hiring a skilled coder who will help bring your vision to life.</p>]]></content><author><name>Matthew Pritchard</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Imposter syndrome can create a ruminating false narrative that your efforts will end in adverse outcomes, especially when you’re starting as a CTO or fractional CTO. As a leader, this is the last scenario you want. Part of your role is to set up your teams for success. Here are six ways to toss those negative feelings out the window and set you on the path toward preserving the road to success.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/medium-shot-smiley-programmer-indoors.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/medium-shot-smiley-programmer-indoors.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">8 Biggest Challenges Tech Recruiters Face in 2023</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/04/05/8-biggest-challenges-tech-recruiters-face-in-2023/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="8 Biggest Challenges Tech Recruiters Face in 2023" /><published>2023-04-05T20:04:17+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-05T20:04:17+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/04/05/8-biggest-challenges-tech-recruiters-face-in-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/04/05/8-biggest-challenges-tech-recruiters-face-in-2023/"><![CDATA[<p>In 2023, tech recruiters are watching their competitors snatch top talent. They also compete with job seekers’ shifting priorities. These priorities are encouraging digital leaders to become more proactive. They are aligning their people strategy with their business strategy, expanding their talent pool, and making new efforts to understand employees’ wants.</p>

<p>Yet, they are also weighing economic factors. While tech recruiters realize the demand for <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/30/why-demand-for-tech-talent-is-so-high/">tech solutions and products will persevere</a>, they are still dealing with persistent hiring challenges from the previous year and an abundance of new ones.</p>

<h2 id="1-evaluating-skills"><strong>1. Evaluating Skills</strong></h2>

<p>Tech leaders need a highly skilled workforce to keep up with the pace of change within the digital environment. The <a href="https://www.weforum.org/press/2020/01/the-reskilling-revolution-better-skills-better-jobs-better-education-for-a-billion-people-by-2030/">World Economic Forum reports </a>that technological advancements will radically transform numerous jobs. Globalization and COVID-19-related industry shifts will also make an impact. The international organization warned that core skills for many jobs would change in 2022, and if trends like this continue, outdated education will worsen the skills mismatch.</p>

<p>Currently, employers are taking steps to align their workforce with their business objectives. They are identifying their company’s critical skills and assessing skill needs to expand and retain talent. This clarity can help them determine gaps, overlaps, training, and pathways to progression so employees can quickly and easily transition to high-skilled roles. As a result, they are reskilling and upskilling their employees. In addition, they are having recruiters focus less on degrees and more on skills during the hiring process.</p>

<h2 id="2-employee-retention">2. Employee Retention</h2>

<p>Employers are still finding ways to mitigate the impact of the Great Resignation and quiet quitting. Workers are still leaving their jobs at a steady rate due to an unpleasant work environment or burnout. And, if they aren’t quitting, they are doing their work at the bare minimum. This type of low engagement costs the world economy $7.8 billion, according to<a href="https://www.gallup.com/workplace/349484/state-of-the-global-workplace-2022-report.aspx?thank-you-report-form=1"> Gallup’s State of the Global Workplace: 2022 Report</a>.</p>

<p>Employers are responding using an old method but with a new name, “quiet hiring,” which means tech recruiters don’t have to look outside the company for promising talent. Instead, they are helping to fill jobs internally. They identify workers doing their regular job and taking on additional tasks related to a vacant position. Ultimately, the employee gets promoted, and the employer saves money on hiring and training costs.</p>

<p>Tech recruiters can ask more questions about a job candidate’s motivations and career goals during the hiring process to help improve employee retention. They can also gather actionable feedback from current employees, such as employee satisfaction surveys.</p>

<h2 id="3-economic-uncertainty">3. Economic Uncertainty</h2>

<p>Business executives are attempting to navigate an uncertain economic environment. Members of the National Association for Business Economics participating in a<a href="https://nabe.com/NABE/Surveys/Business_Conditions_Surveys/January-2023-Business-Conditions-Survey-Summary.aspx"> January 2023 survey</a> gauged the likelihood of a recession at more than 50 percent. The volatility has produced predictions ranging from a recession to robust growth. Despite persistent high inflation, supply chain bottlenecks, and rising commodity and energy prices, the economy has experienced substantial gains. For example, consumer spending started the year off strong.</p>

<p>Some tech companies are slowing the pace of hiring and moving around resources in response to the uncertainty and hoping to stay resilient.<a href="https://www.cfo.com/resources/2023/02/cfos-2023-outlook-cautious-optimism-amid-recession-cost-cutting-workforce-challenges/"> A survey of CFOS, C-Suite executives, and managers</a> that CFO.com shared revealed that nearly all of the respondents planned to make budget cuts. Three out of five anticipated reducing costs associated with hiring and retaining talent despite critical first-quarter hiring needs. Business managers are considering cost-effective learning strategies, such as mentorships, to position workers so they are adequate for present needs and well-positioned for future roles.</p>

<p>Tech recruiters can continue to hire the best talent with the best skills. Some are doing this by changing their <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/01/14/is-your-approach-to-hiring-wrong/">hiring approach</a> and hiring contractors.</p>

<h2 id="4-diversity-and-inclusion">4. Diversity and Inclusion</h2>

<p>Diversity and inclusion remain a priority for new hires. More than a third of participants responding to a<a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/\~/media/mckinsey/business%20functions/people%20and%20organizational%20performance/our%20insights/understanding%20organizational%20barriers%20to%20a%20more%20inclusive%20workplace/understanding-organizational-barriers-to-a-more-inclusive-workplace.pdf?shouldIndex=false"> McKinsey Global Survey</a> revealed that they didn’t pursue a job because they believed the organization lacked an inclusive workplace. They also wanted to see employers advance diversity and inclusion in the workplace. Some suggestions they shared included holding conversations recognizing the need for inclusion, taking action that improves efforts and behaviors, and setting goals for underrepresented groups in recruitment, succession planning, and sponsorship programs.</p>

<p>More management teams are taking note. In 2020, companies worldwide spent an estimated $7.5 billion on diversity, equity, and inclusion, which is projected to double by 2026,<a href="https://www3.weforum.org/docs/WEF_Global_Parity_Alliance_2023.pdf"> according to the Global Parity Alliance</a>. However, the cross-industry group committed to advancing DEI also noticed that the pace could be faster even though progress is occurring. So, it launched the DEI Lighthouse Programme to promote DEI initiatives. It is an annual effort to find and equip leaders with DEI best practices.</p>

<h2 id="5-right-technology-tools">5. Right Technology Tools</h2>

<p>Rapid technological transformations may leave several business leaders wondering whether their tech tools are enough. Advanced technologies can support new strategies, practices, and innovation from new hires. However, inadequate tech tools pave the way for cybersecurity risks and compliance issues and limit the company’s competitive advantage. As these leaders analyze business issues and process improvements, some realize that their disparate systems limit their strategic responses and business updates.</p>

<p>The massive technological changes are also creating shifts within industries that are helping to expand and accelerate a business’ capabilities and processes. These changes support remote hiring, workflows, upskilling opportunities, and skills assessments.</p>

<p>Employers can consider conducting an IT audit to assess the effectiveness of current technology tools and their ability to minimize business risks. They can also establish the business’s requirements criteria to help make informed purchasing decisions.</p>

<h2 id="6-remote-work">6. Remote Work</h2>

<p>Employers still have difficulty getting workers to return to the office despite a tight labor market. However, workers are now more accustomed to having a flexible work schedule. This change has eased their work-life balance and supported their mental well-being. As a result, they have made remote work options a top priority in their job search.</p>

<p>Remote work is here and will likely stay since it offers <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/03/13/10-remote-work-benefits-and-best-practices-in-2023/">numerous employee and employer benefits</a>. For instance, Companies shore up overhead costs and see improved performance.<a href="https://www.prweb.com/releases/many_u_s_companies_find_productivity_not_negatively_impacted_by_remote_work/prweb19062791.htm"> A 2022 survey</a> conducted by The Harris Poll for Express Employment Professionals found that three in five businesses found that remote work positively impacted the company and didn’t harm their efforts. In addition, business leaders see more engagement and <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/08/05/happy/">job satisfaction</a>.</p>

<p>Tech recruiters will need to pay attention to how job candidates discuss their work style during the hiring process and take note of flexible work preferences, which will allow them to sweeten the deal when making a job offer.</p>

<h2 id="7-compensation-and-benefits-package">7. Compensation and Benefits Package</h2>

<p>Workers emphasize when, where, and how they work during the hiring process. As a result, employers are finding that it’s critical to demonstrate the value of the employee with their compensation and benefits package. It supports not only recruitment but retention. The package enables recruiters the agility to meet workers’ needs. If they cannot meet one factor like a high wage, they can compensate with another incentive, such as more paid time off.</p>

<p>Some companies are letting employees determine their pay package, for instance, choosing cash and stock options. However, employers can revisit and refresh their benefits on an ongoing basis and help employees maximize their use when they make significant changes due to life events, such as marriage or childbirth.</p>

<h2 id="8-competition-outside-of-the-tech-sector">8. Competition Outside of the Tech Sector</h2>

<p>According to a <a href="https://joinhandshake.com/network-trends/2023-forges-ahead/">Handshake Network Trends report</a>, recent college graduates are anxious yet optimistic about their job prospects. The respondents, mostly business and tech majors, sought stability and salary as their top priorities. In addition, members of the class of 2023 applied for jobs sooner. They also kept an eye on Big Tech layoffs. Many graduates expanded their job search to reach other industries and sectors. Recruiters welcome them by looking past the student’s major or school and more at underlying transferable skills that match specific business needs.</p>

<p>The recent tech company layoffs, hiring freezes, and downscaled recruiting efforts have flooded the job market with tech talent, and companies in industries needing their digital skills, such as healthcare, are set to benefit. Some are scooping up top tech talent to help modernize business functions and processes and harness data to improve their services. Tech workers also see advantages; they can broaden their expertise and skill set by solving new types of problems.</p>

<p>Some tech recruiters pick up new talent and shape new ones by not requiring a four-year college degree. It’s a result of many tech companies’ efforts to fast-pace the hiring process and erase the supply-demand imbalance. Some have added apprenticeship programs and have partnered with community colleges.</p>

<p>After a series of economic, social, and political shifts, business leaders understand the need to stay agile. As a result, they are skirting labor issues with strategies to enhance talent sourcing and placing and placing more focus on aspects like culture, compensation, and work-life balance. Likewise, tech recruiters are navigating the talent acquisition challenges and heeding the people-first effort to produce an efficient hiring process that yields results.</p>]]></content><author><name>Brigitte Yuille Ayerves Valderas</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recruiting leading talent continues to be a problem within tech in 2023. With more open positions than qualified talent, technical recruiting grows even more complicated as the year unfolds. For any organization looking to hire developers, it's a complex landscape.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-cottonbro-studio-5989927.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-cottonbro-studio-5989927.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">10 Remote Work Benefits and Best Practices in 2023</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/03/13/10-remote-work-benefits-and-best-practices-in-2023/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="10 Remote Work Benefits and Best Practices in 2023" /><published>2023-03-13T17:35:57+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-13T17:35:57+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/03/13/10-remote-work-benefits-and-best-practices-in-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/03/13/10-remote-work-benefits-and-best-practices-in-2023/"><![CDATA[<p>Opportunities to work from home have ballooned over the past few years, and technological advancements are making the arrangements more attainable for workers and employers.</p>

<p>While remote work is still evolving, it’s creating alterations in work options and styles in relation to occupation and geography. Workers are enjoying more freedom and taking control of their work life. Employers are able to reduce their expenses and expand their talent reach and talent pool. They are also becoming more proactive about supporting their workers’ well-being.</p>

<p>In addition, remote work is tossing out some traditional job boundaries. These changes are giving employers the chance to experiment with new approaches in the digital workplace. Their efforts and new innovations are ultimately making working from home a permanent change.</p>

<p>Here are ten benefits and best practices of remote work.</p>

<h2 id="1-flexible-work-options"><strong>1. Flexible Work Options</strong></h2>

<p>Job candidates have placed workplace flexibility among their top priorities, according to the <a href="https://business.linkedin.com/talent-solutions/global-talent-trends">2022 Global Talent Trends report</a> released by LinkedIn.</p>

<p>Working from home makes it easier for workers to tackle errands and find time to attend events. Employers that let workers create their own schedules allow them to visit the doctor, take care of their vehicle and household repairs, attend their child’s school event, or manage childcare without worrying that their time away from work could negatively impact their job.</p>

<p>The flexibility enables workers to work from home, pack their laptops, and <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/09/12/how-coworking-spaces-have-helped-the-shift-toward-remote-hybrid-work/">venture elsewhere</a>. For example, they may work at a relative’s or vacation home to avoid cramped settings and noisy neighbors. Or, they may become “digital nomads” and align their work schedules with their personal travel itinerary.</p>

<p>However, employers also get some perks too. They can <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/12/07/how-to-work-specialized-recruiting-into-your-hiring-strategy/">snag competitive talent</a> and keep their top performers longer with <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/02/15/10-ways-2023-is-impacting-hiring/">flexible work options</a>. Flexible arrangements allow them to expand their search for new employees. In addition, they can diversify their workforce to accelerate innovation.</p>

<p>When setting up flexible work options, discussing expectations and boundaries for work hours and communication is essential. Sometimes, a worker may need to stagger their hours to avoid distractions in the home, such as children or a spouse on a call. In addition, consider setting up regular check-ins to help keep the work on track and communication flowing.</p>

<h2 id="2-boosted-productivity"><strong>2. Boosted Productivity</strong></h2>

<p>Chatty coworkers, personal phone conversations from a coworker in the next cubicle, ringing phones, chimes from alerts and notifications, and copy machines or printers are among the distractions that occur in the workplace. Remote work avoids those issues and lets workers create a more productive work environment at home because they can find the time and place that will help maximize their output.</p>

<p>Workers with a fully flexible schedule showed 29 percent higher productivity compared to those who couldn’t adjust to their shift, according to the <a href="https://futureforum.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Future-Forum-Pulse-Report-Fall-2022.pdf0/Future-Forum-Pulse-Report-Fall-2022.pdf">2022 Future Forum Pulse survey</a>. The survey questioned more than 10,000 workers throughout the world. It also found that half of the fully remote respondents were able to improve their focus.</p>

<p>Remote work gives workers more work-life balance, which can help them pace their work, so they produce consistent, high-quality results and avoid burnout. In addition, workers can organize unique workstyles that help them address their assignments at peak performance time and care for their family and physical and emotional health.</p>

<p>Employers can discover and experiment with productivity tools to determine what works for their teams. They can also motivate workers with recognition and rewards, offer support for professional development and help workers set goals to drive better performance.</p>

<p>Workers can boost their productivity by learning the hours throughout the day when they have the most energy and the least distractions. This assessment will also help them determine how they schedule their tasks and choose when to tackle their most cognitively demanding ones.</p>

<h3 id="3-reduced-stress-levels"><strong>3. Reduced Stress Levels</strong></h3>

<p>Workers can bypass the congestion of inner city transport systems and other traffic-clogged roads when they work from home. They also cut out long commutes and crowded transit stations. As a result, they avoid stressful situations and can reallocate their time to support a healthier work-life balance.</p>

<p>At home, workers gain more control over how they do their work and design settings conducive to productivity and relaxation. For example, they can create or seek out quieter and more comfortable environments.</p>

<p>In addition, remote workers may enjoy some reprieve from the unpleasant aspects of the company culture, such as gossip and cliques, helping them to focus more on their job. A <a href="https://mhanational.org/sites/default/files/Mind%20the%20Workplace%20-%20MHA%20Workplace%20Health%20Survey%202017%20FINAL%209.13.pdf">Mental Health America study</a> of 17,000 workers found that negative work environments can contribute to higher rates of absenteeism, conflict in personal relationships, and unhealthy behaviors like alcohol or substance abuse. While workers can not avoid all workplace stressors, working from home can give them more flexibility and control regarding how to deal with them.</p>

<p>Remote workers can structure their day to limit distractions. For example, they can create a routine that includes regular breaks, exercise, and lunch times. Workers can also schedule their social interactions in a way that lets them maintain and make new connections.</p>

<p>As workers’ stress levels subside, employers reap the benefits. The workers become more engaged and satisfied with their job, which enhances the company’s culture and productivity.</p>

<h2 id="4-cost-savings"><strong>4. Cost Savings</strong></h2>

<p>Employers can achieve more cost savings with remote workers. They can circumvent costs like office supplies and equipment, utility fees, janitorial services, security, parking spaces, and rental fees. In addition, remote work is becoming a valuable bargaining chip for employers looking for ways to retain employees without increasing pay. Employers can also save money on turnover because of job satisfaction.</p>

<p>The research firm <a href="https://globalworkplaceanalytics.com/cut-oil">Global Workplace Analytics</a> found that telework can save companies $500 billion a year. The reduced costs resulted from real estate, electricity, absenteeism, turnover, and productivity. Ultimately, businesses can pocket more than $11,000 per employee per year, and this savings is if employees worked only half of the time from home.</p>

<p>Workers realize cost savings as they either reduce or eliminate their gas, vehicle maintenance and insurance, wardrobe fees, and childcare costs. Staying at home avoids those quick stopovers to get coffee and expensive lunch meals at the cafeteria or with coworkers. <a href="https://globalworkplaceanalytics.com/telecommuting-statistics">Global Workplace Analytics </a>has estimated that employees working at home half the time can save between $600 and $6,000 per year.</p>

<p>Workers can start conserving their money by stocking up on nutritious foods and storing ready-to-heat-leftovers to avoid the temptation of getting unhealthy takeout meals. Coffee lovers should invest in setting up their coffee station to avoid runs to the coffee shop. Workers can also monitor work-related expenses they can claim as home office deductions.</p>

<h2 id="5-improved-work-life-management"><strong>5. Improved Work-Life Management</strong></h2>

<p>Working from home can make it easier to manage the day, especially for parents and caregivers who can focus on strengthening their relationships with their loved ones.</p>

<p>Since they gain time from not having a daily work commute, workers can get up later and put away a pile of laundry or dishes in between virtual meetings. They can carve out the time to go to routine medical appointments or attend an event at their child’s school without worrying about jeopardizing their job. They can show up and be more present in their personal relationships. The COVID-19 pandemic created at-home work environments where spouses or partners worked side by side, and parents set up digital classrooms for their kids nearby to help monitor their progress.</p>

<p>Volunteerism is one way employers can encourage social interaction and social action. They can also suggest workers focus on making their time more productive rather than putting in additional hours and checking in their workload. Fitness stipends, different options for childcare support, and mental health support are some perks companies can add.</p>

<p>Workers can effectively reach their work-life management goals by establishing routines and work schedules with a clear start and end time. They can ensure their work area is separate from living spaces in their home to avoid the temptation to check their email. They can also invest in ergonomic desk furniture. Most importantly, taking breaks for walks and letting their eyes rest can help them maintain a healthy lifestyle.</p>

<h2 id="6-increased-degree-of-autonomy"><strong>6. Increased degree of autonomy</strong></h2>

<p>Remote workers can choose how they want to go about their day and perform their tasks with less oversight. They don’t have to worry about someone peeking over their shoulder at their screen and micromanagers continuously stopping by their cubicle or holding impromptu meetings to get a pulse on their work activities.</p>

<p>Instead, workers can find a work rhythm that lets them function effectively and take breaks to refresh and develop new ideas. As a result, autonomy can boost work performance because it empowers workers to grow, trust their skills and capabilities, and make confident decisions. It can also help reduce stress and lead to better job satisfaction.</p>

<p>Giving workers autonomy fosters greater responsibility, engagement, creativity, and motivation. For employers, these attributes can result in more productive teams and a successful organization. Employers can promote autonomy by encouraging their workers to attend workshops and invest in training and skill development to empower their ability to work responsibly and independently. They can also establish boundaries via project management and audio or visual check-ins.</p>

<h2 id="7-more-collaborative-culture"><strong>7. More Collaborative Culture</strong></h2>

<p>Remote work requires finding alternative communication methods since many social cues are missing, such as body language and vocal tone. These cues are necessary to ensure the normal pace and structure of conversations. Video conferencing and team collaboration technologies, like Zoom and Teams, and project management programs became essential during the COVID-19 pandemic and have helped support teamwork and team-building activities.</p>

<p>Many of these technologies have mobile apps that can keep workers connected, especially when running errands or waiting for appointments. For instance, workers can easily hop from their laptops to their smartphones. Video conferencing technologies increase engagement because people see their coworkers all at once on the screen, and they receive content at the same time.</p>

<p>Both employers and employees can create virtual team-building rituals, such as celebrations and socializing events, to <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/08/18/remote-team-retreats-8-reasons-why-your-company-needs-one/">strengthen work relationships</a>. They should also ensure their messages are clear to avoid misinterpretation, even if it means writing a longer email.</p>

<h2 id="8-lessened-environmental-impact"><strong>8. Lessened Environmental Impact</strong></h2>

<p>The benefits of workers doing their job from home can support them, their employers, and the overall global efforts to protect the environment. In 2019, the <a href="https://www.census.gov/newsroom/press-releases/2021/one-way-travel-time-to-work-rises.html">U.S. Census Bureau reported</a> that the average one-way work commute in the U.S. was 27.6 minutes. Remote work helps reduce greenhouse gas emissions by reducing cars on the road and traffic congestion, which can lead to a buildup of pollutants.</p>

<p>Employers can conserve energy and reduce waste, helping to curb their carbon footprint within the office space. Since companies can cut costs, they can reallocate their budgets. Employers maintaining office space can use natural lights, reduce heating and increase cooling temperatures, clean filters, and check for eligible tax breaks.</p>

<p>Workers can consider clean energy sources to help reduce expenses, such as installing solar panels. Meanwhile, simple actions like turning off their computer or putting it into sleep mode and not ordering takeout can help reduce waste and their carbon footprint, especially since some food establishments may use plastic for packaging their food.</p>

<h2 id="9-a-more-accessible-and-inclusive-workplace"><strong>9. A More Accessible and Inclusive Workplace</strong></h2>

<p>Remote work creates more job opportunities for people living with disabilities. They can avoid barriers and obstacles in office settings and during their daily commute. Remote work has helped individuals with compromised immune systems reduce their exposure to illnesses like COVID-19, RSV, and the flu. It also helps people suffering from specific mental issues like anxiety because it can limit social interactions and noisy distractions, such as random chimes and computer ping notifications.</p>

<p>In addition, working from home allows workers with disabilities to customize their environments to meet their personalized needs and take advantage of the flexibility to schedule appointments.</p>

<p>Let’s face it. Events come up in life that can change circumstances. For example, a car accident may have landed a worker in the hospital, or they may have to take time to care for a loved one. Remote work helps employers retain employees when unforeseen or unfortunate events arise. It also <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/14/how-talent-sourcing-can-solve-your-diversity-problem/">diversifies the talent pool</a> creating more diversity of thought.</p>

<p>Employers can create open and honest communication by empathizing and asking what accommodations are needed for their workers. For example, they can clearly communicate which deadlines are flexible and which are not. Employers can also support workers with disabilities by providing a stipend to help set up their environment for specific equipment and promoting wellness programs that can focus on meditation, breathwork, and self-care remedies. Accommodating overlooked and underrepresented communities can encourage more productivity and job satisfaction, which can produce more results.</p>

<h2 id="10-higher-job-satisfaction"><strong>10. Higher Job Satisfaction</strong></h2>

<p>Working from home can provide an instant <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/08/05/happy/">boost in job satisfaction</a>. Workers don’t have to power through their day in the confines of their office. Instead, they can take more productive breaks that include exercise and meditation.</p>

<p>According to the annual <a href="https://mediacenter.adp.com/2022-04-25-ADP-Research-Institute-R-Reveals-Pandemic-Sparked-Shift-in-Workers-Priorities-and-Expectations-in-New-Global-Study">ADPRI “People at Work 2022: A Global Workforce View” survey</a>, 89 percent of respondents working from home expressed more optimism about the next five years compared to peers who had to report to the office. Nearly half of them indicated that it made it easier to parent. The survey questioned 32,000 workers from 17 countries. Two-thirds of the participants indicated that they would consider looking for a new job if required to return to the office full-time.</p>

<p>Employers can help maintain job satisfaction through acknowledgment and recognition programs. They can also show appreciation for activities like taking on additional projects through praise in newsletters and other internal communication channels like Slack. In addition, employers can send out short surveys to get feedback about the work environment to learn what’s working well and what needs improvement.</p>

<p>Remote work can be a win-win for workers and employers as long as they set clear standards and expectations.</p>

<p>Workers need to choose a productive work area with limited distractions, set a schedule and establish a routine that allows them to take breaks to eat, exercise, socialize with colleagues, and recharge.</p>

<p>Employers must evaluate the job roles workers can do partly from home and which ones the workers can do fully remote. Then, they should adapt to workers’ needs by making available resources that support their productivity and mental health. They should also request feedback more frequently to help improve work experiences and create policies that support optimal performance. Employers must also keep an eye on the technological and workplace trends that support remote work.</p>]]></content><author><name>Brigitte Yuille Ayerves Valderas</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover the advantages of remote work for both employers and employees with these ten benefits and best practices. Enjoy flexible work options that prioritize work-life balance and increase productivity, while reducing stress and cutting down on costs. Join the millions of workers worldwide who have made working from home a permanent change.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-ivan-samkov-4238488.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-ivan-samkov-4238488.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">10 Ways 2023 is Impacting Hiring</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/02/15/10-ways-2023-is-impacting-hiring/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="10 Ways 2023 is Impacting Hiring" /><published>2023-02-15T19:53:52+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-15T19:53:52+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/02/15/10-ways-2023-is-impacting-hiring</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/02/15/10-ways-2023-is-impacting-hiring/"><![CDATA[<p>At the start of 2023, headlines shifted from the Great Resignation to layoffs. However, job seekers are likely to maintain more power than they think, as the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/02/03/business/economy/jobs-report-january-2023.html">labor market remains strong</a> and demand for tech employment remains high. Despite the layoff surge from Big Tech such as Microsoft, Google (Alphabet), Meta, and Salesforce, they only represent a portion of the tech industry. Many opportunities still exist, particularly for all <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/money/economy/2023/02/07/tech-layoffs-2023-google-amazon/11135692002/">small to medium-sized tech companies</a> needing tech expertise.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, workers <a href="https://www.statista.com/chart/26186/number-of-people-quitting-their-jobs-in-the-united-states/#:\~:text=U.S.%20labor%20market&amp;text=According%20to%20the%20latest%20JOLTS,for%202022%20to%2046.6%20million.">have continued to leave their jobs</a> to look for companies that align more with flexible lifestyles and provide a greater sense of purpose, well-being, and skills growth. With a strong job market and the ongoing shift to appease workers’ desires for flexible, remote, and hybrid workplaces, leaders are still undertaking the best ways to manage their workforce. Here are some of the ongoing trends for 2023 that companies are focused on to attract A-list employees and leverage top-performing freelancers in the modern workplace.</p>

<h3 id="1-well-being-remains-a-top-priority-for-employee-retention"><strong>1. Well-being Remains a Top Priority for Employee Retention</strong></h3>

<p>Mental, physical, and sound financial health are the main drivers for employee retention. Top priorities for 2023 include human leadership training to support a human workplace. According to a recent <a href="https://www.gartner.com/en/newsroom/press-releases/2022-10-12-gartner-survey-reveals-leader-and-manager-effectiveness-tops-hr-leaders-list-of-priorities-for-2023">Gartner Report</a>, “This is a priority for 60% of HR leaders, and 24% say their leadership development approach does not prepare leaders for the future of work”. What makes up human leadership? Gartner Research has identified the following:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Authentic</strong>: Act with purpose and enable true self-expression for themselves and their teams.</li>
  <li><strong>Empathetic</strong>: Show genuine care, respect, and concern for employees’ well-being.</li>
  <li><strong>Adaptive</strong>: Enable flexibility and support that fits team members’ unique needs.</li>
</ul>

<p>While these qualities have always been important, top performers consider the above leadership components vital to their work contribution and engagement.</p>

<p>Organizations with <a href="https://www.gartner.com/en/newsroom/press-releases/06-23-22-gartner-hr-research-identifies-human-leadership-as-the-next-evolution-of-leadership">more human leaders will have higher engagement and less turnover</a>. Employees show higher engagement rates when reporting to human leaders versus employees who don’t consider their leadership to be practicing human leadership qualities. Highly engaged employees improve team performance by up to 27%, leading to more revenue and higher profitability.</p>

<h3 id="2-employers-continue-to-focus-on-remote-and-hybrid-work">2. <strong>Employers Continue to Focus on Remote and Hybrid Work</strong></h3>

<p>The trend for creating human workplaces with remote and hybrid work options remains strong, even though some companies demand their employees return to the office full-time. Many organizations know that pressing their <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/robinryan/2023/01/10/heres-whats-happening-to-remote-work-in-2023/?sh=22c70e5979d9">workforce to return to the office</a> will exacerbate turnover rates. According to Gallup, more than half of Americans can work remotely, and <a href="https://www.gallup.com/workplace/397751/returning-office-current-preferred-future-state-remote-work.aspx">up to 60% want a long-term hybrid option</a>.</p>

<p>Employers are focusing on making their organizations more adaptable to the fluid-changing business conditions. <a href="https://www.gallup.com/workplace/468173/workplace-findings-leaders-need-navigate-year.aspx">Gallup also noted</a> that nearly one-third of employees would more than likely look for work elsewhere if their employer didn’t offer an option to work remotely. Companies are listening, and several organizations are planning to design a workforce that reflects a combination of workplace options, such as:</p>

<ul>
  <li>55% fully hybrid workers</li>
  <li>22% fully remote workers</li>
  <li>23% fully on-site workers</li>
</ul>

<p>Flexible, hybrid, and remote work models give employees more opportunities to strike a work-life balance. They have more time to manage their lives between family, friends, and physical and social activities that support overall well-being. The time savings on commutes and gas, parking, and public transportation costs during sharp increases in inflation give workers a chance to save money.</p>

<h3 id="3-dei-continues-to-drive-talent-acquisition-and-retention"><strong>3. DEI Continues to Drive Talent Acquisition and Retention</strong></h3>

<p>Companies with Diversity Equity and Inclusion (DEI) initiatives aim to produce more equitable outcomes. They address systematic inequality and ensure fair treatment and opportunities for all employees attracting and retaining the best and the brightest.</p>

<p>A diverse and inclusive workplace attracts a broader pool of candidates in a tight employment market where a highly skilled workforce is in high demand. Companies promoting positive and inclusive human workplaces where all employees feel valued, respected, and heard will attract and retain top performers.</p>

<p>Employees are more likely to stay with a company that values and respects them. When employees feel included and valued, they’re more likely to be engaged and satisfied with their work, improving morale and performance. <a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/featured-insights/diversity-and-inclusion/diversity-wins-how-inclusion-matters">McKinsey &amp; Company’s 2020 Diversity Wins report</a> underlines DEI as a significant driver for better business results and financial performance over time.</p>

<p>Diverse companies provide a more comprehensive range of perspectives, which leads to more effective decision-making. Diversity helps companies find solutions to problems that might otherwise go unsolved if they had been tasked with a group of people who think alike. Effective decisions lead to efficient processes and innovative solutions, boosting creativity and productivity.</p>

<p>Companies focusing on DEI best practices also provide better customer service because they accurately reflect a diverse population driving brand loyalty. A Deloitte study <a href="https://www2.deloitte.com/us/en/insights/topics/marketing-and-sales-operations/global-marketing-trends/2022/diversity-and-inclusion-in-marketing.html">found that 57% of consumers are more loyal to brands that commit to addressing social inequities</a> in their actions.</p>

<p>Consequently, companies with strong DEI practices improve a company’s reputation. They create more positive and productive work environments while positioning themselves as industry leaders. As a result, DEI-leading companies reduce turnover, increase engagement and drive revenue.</p>

<h3 id="4-purpose-driven-employers-remain-a-top-talent-choice">4. <strong>Purpose-Driven Employers Remain a Top Talent Choice</strong></h3>

<p>In 2023 purpose-driven employers are better positioned to attract top talent and younger Gen Z workers in a tight employment market. As more and more employees want to have a purpose within their work. Purpose-driven employers also provide more significant opportunities for growth.</p>

<p><a href="https://www2.deloitte.com/us/en/insights/topics/marketing-and-sales-operations/global-marketing-trends/2020/purpose-driven-companies.html">According to Deloitte</a>, “Purpose-driven companies witness higher market share gains and grow three times faster on average than their competitors, all while achieving higher workforce and customer satisfaction.” They’re often mission-driven and give their employees opportunities to develop new skills and take on new challenges helping them grow personally and professionally.</p>

<p>So it’s not surprising that organizations are looking for ways to align their purpose with their employees’ personal and professional aspirations. They understand that their employees are a source of growth. Studies from <a href="https://www.gallup.com/workplace/236927/employee-engagement-drives-growth.aspx">Gallup</a> show that employees who feel a strong sense of purpose and connection to their employer are more likely to be engaged, motivated, and productive, leading to company hire earnings.</p>

<p>The Gallup study also shows that high employee engagement boosts retention. Low-engagement teams typically <a href="https://www.gallup.com/workplace/236927/employee-engagement-drives-growth.aspx">endure turnover rates that are 18% to 43% higher</a> than highly engaged teams. Employees are less likely to look for other work during economic uncertainty.</p>

<h3 id="5-employees-still-want-upskilling-and-reskilling-opportunities">5. <strong>Employees Still Want Upskilling and Reskilling Opportunities</strong></h3>

<p>In the rapidly changing job market, upskilling and reskilling are increasingly important for employers to attract and retain a highly skilled workforce. Many companies are investing in their employees by providing opportunities to develop new skills and enhance their existing ones.</p>

<p>One way employers provide upskilling and reskilling is through training programs and workshops. These programs cover a wide range of topics, from new technologies to soft skills like leadership and teamwork. Employers are also investing in employees through online learning platforms offering various courses and certifications.</p>

<p>The following are examples of companies that have implemented successful upskilling and reskilling programs.</p>

<p>IBM has a comprehensive reskilling program it launched to provide <a href="https://newsroom.ibm.com/2021-10-13-IBM-Commits-to-Skill-30-Million-People-Globally-by-2030">30 million people with new skills needed for the jobs of tomorrow </a>by 2030. The program offers employees access to thousands of online courses and certifications. This program has helped IBM stay ahead of the technological curve and allowed its employees to develop their skills continually.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Amazon provides a variety of training and development programs for its employees, including its <a href="https://www.amazoncareerchoice.com/home">“Career Choice”</a> program, which pays for employees to take courses in fields that are in high demand. This program has helped Amazon attract and retain skilled employees, which has resulted in improved productivity and job satisfaction.</li>
  <li>Accenture’s <a href="https://s2sacademy.org/login/">“Skills to Succeed”</a> program focuses on helping employees develop the skills they need to succeed in the digital economy. This program includes online courses, certifications, and hands-on projects that allow employees to gain practical experience. As a result of the program, Accenture has been able to attract and retain a highly skilled workforce.</li>
</ul>

<p>These programs have helped companies attract and retain a highly skilled workforce, leading to increased productivity and improved job satisfaction.</p>

<p>Upskilling and reskilling initiatives help employees grow professionally and help companies stay competitive in the job market. Employers who invest in their employees will reap the rewards of increased productivity, improved job satisfaction, and a stronger, more skilled workforce</p>

<h3 id="6-employers-are-leveraging-data-driven-recruitment">6. <strong>Employers are Leveraging Data-Driven Recruitment</strong></h3>

<p>Artificial intelligence (AI) revolutionizes how organizations recruit and hire new talent. In the past, the recruitment process was largely manual and relied heavily on intuition and guesswork. But with the advent of AI, organizations can now leverage data-driven insights to make more informed and objective hiring decisions. The[ AI market expects to expand to US$1,597 billion by 2030](https://www.precedenceresearch.com/artificial-intelligence-market#:~:text=The%20global%20artificial%20intelligence%20(AI,USD%20147.58%20billion%20in%202021.).</p>

<p>AI accesses data-driven recruitment through the use of machine learning algorithms. Machine learning algorithms analyze large amounts of data and identify patterns and correlations that would be difficult for humans to detect. For example, an AI-powered recruitment platform can analyze resumes, job descriptions, and candidate performance data to identify the essential skills and qualifications for a particular role. This information can create targeted recruitment campaigns, streamline the application review process, and determine the best candidates.</p>

<p>Another way AI leverages data-driven recruitment is by automating specific tasks that recruiters and hiring managers perform. For instance, an AI-powered platform can automatically screen resumes and applications, eliminating the need for manual review. It can also automate the scheduling of interviews and provide real-time feedback to candidates, saving the recruiter’s time and effort. It also helps to reduce bias and ensure a more objective and fair selection process.</p>

<p>AI can also personalize the recruitment experience for both candidates and recruiters. For example, AI-powered platforms can suggest job openings matching a candidate’s skills and knowledge, reducing their time to search for the proper role.</p>

<p>Finally, AI can investigate the performance of a company’s recruitment efforts and identify areas for improvement. For instance, an AI-powered platform can analyze the time-to-hire, cost-per-hire, and candidate experience metrics, providing recruiters with actionable insights to improve the efficiency and effectiveness of their recruitment process.</p>

<p>Ultimately, AI makes the entire recruitment process more efficient and convenient. It helps organizations to make more informed and objective hiring decisions, improving the candidate experience and finding the best talent for an organization.</p>

<h3 id="7-demand-for-freelancers-grows">7. <strong>Demand for Freelancers Grows</strong></h3>

<p>Freelancing is a growing trend. In 2023 up to <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/jonyounger/2022/12/22/the-trends-shaping-the-freelance-revolution-in-2023/?sh=70fc975222a3">78% of companies are expected to hire freelancers</a> versus adding staff. Companies rely on more contract and freelance workers to meet short-term business needs. Freelancers offer businesses access to a broader pool of talent and expertise, which is becoming increasingly important in a fast-changing job market. Companies working with freelancers can quickly and easily bring in specific skills and experience as needed without having to invest in full-time employees.</p>

<p>Many companies have found that freelancers are a flexible and cost-effective solution for filling skills gaps, particularly during economic uncertainty. Hiring freelancers is a way to reduce costs and manage workforce expenses more effectively.</p>

<p>Overall, the need for businesses to stay competitive and adapt to changing market conditions drives the demand for freelancers. Companies leveraging the benefits of freelancers can adapt to changing market conditions and meet the challenges of the latest job market.</p>

<h3 id="8-talent-experience-platform-adoption-continues">8. <strong>Talent Experience Platform Adoption Continues</strong></h3>

<p>The adoption of Talent Experience Platforms (TXP) continues to impact the hiring landscape in 2023. TXPs are becoming increasingly popular as organizations look for ways to improve the candidate experience and streamline recruitment processes.</p>

<p>TXP solutions provide HR organizations with a centralized platform to bring all the tools and processes needed to manage talent acquisition. From job postings and candidate sourcing to interviewing and offer management. TXPs encompasses content, learning, and analytics, driving employee unity and engagement with the following benefits:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Improved candidate experience:</strong> TXP solution provide a more seamless and user-friendly experience for candidates.</li>
  <li><strong>Increased efficiency:</strong> Saving HR organizations time and reducing errors, TXP solutions automate many of the manual tasks involved in recruitment.</li>
  <li><strong>Better data and analytics:</strong> With all the recruitment data in one place, TXP solutions provide HR organizations with powerful insights into their talent acquisition processes, which helps inform decision-making and drive continuous improvement.</li>
  <li><strong>Improved collaboration:</strong> TXP solutions bring together stakeholders for the recruitment process. Fostering cooperation between HR, hiring managers, and associated teams, resulting in better communication and engaging outcomes.</li>
</ul>

<p>Ultimately the adoption of TXPs is changing the hiring landscape providing HR organizations with the tools and processes they need to improve the candidate experience, increase efficiency, and provide better data and analytics.</p>

<h3 id="9-alumni-networks-continue-to-make-an-impact">9. <strong>Alumni Networks Continue to Make an Impact</strong></h3>

<p>In 2023, corporate alumni networks will be seen as a <a href="https://www.gartner.com/en/articles/9-future-of-work-trends-for-2023">valuable alternative tool</a> for HR organizations. They’re a way for companies to leverage former employees for recruitment.</p>

<p>Alumni networks can help maintain seasoned relationships with employees and tap into their expertise and personal networks. They aim to keep former employees connected with their previous employees, providing an opportunity to attract experienced professionals back to the organization.</p>

<p>These networks can benefit companies looking to fill a skills gap or seek experienced talent. Internal HR departments are finding alumni platforms and networks to be effective because they:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Foster brand loyalty:</strong> Alumni networks help to build brand loyalty and maintain positive relationships with key talent.</li>
  <li><strong>Create a talent pipeline:</strong> They provide a pool of talented individuals HR organizations can tap into when they need to fill a position.</li>
  <li><strong>Promote mentorship and career development:</strong> Connecting former employees with current employees can help promote mentorship and career development, leading to better retention and stronger employee engagement.</li>
  <li><strong>Enhance brand reputation:</strong> Companies with solid alumni networks are often seen as having a positive workplace culture and a commitment to employee development, ultimately enhancing a company’s reputation and attracting top talent.</li>
</ul>

<p>Overall, corporate alumni networks are helping organizations attract top talent and improve their hiring outcomes.</p>

<h3 id="10-salary-transparency-gains-more-traction">10. <strong>Salary Transparency Gains More Traction</strong></h3>

<p>Salary transparency is becoming increasingly important in the <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90830348/more-states-adopt-salary-transparency-in-2023-but-some-companies-still-skirt-the-laws">hiring process for 2023</a> moving towards more open and honest compensation practices. Many organizations recognize the following benefits salary transparency practices offer.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Promotes fairness and equality:</strong> By being transparent about compensation, companies can ensure that they are paying their employees fairly and equitably. This can help to reduce pay disparities and promote a more level playing field for all employees.</li>
  <li><strong>Attracts top talent</strong>: Candidates are more likely to be interested in working for a transparent company about compensation. This helps them make informed decisions about their career paths and ensures fair payment.</li>
  <li><strong>Increases employee satisfaction and engagement:</strong> When employees clearly understand their compensation and the factors that determine their pay, they are more likely to be satisfied with their jobs and engaged in their work.</li>
  <li><strong>Manages expectations:</strong> Salary transparency can help to manage expectations and reduce negotiating time and effort. By being open about compensation, HR organizations can save time and resources that would otherwise be spent negotiating salaries and benefits.</li>
  <li><strong>Supports legal compliance:</strong> Salary transparency is a legal requirement in some countries, and companies must be transparent about compensation to comply with labor laws and regulations.</li>
</ul>

<p>Companies’ transparency about compensation can improve their hiring outcomes and support their employees in making informed career decisions.</p>

<p>While no one can fully predict final hiring outcomes for 2023, insightful organizational leaders wanting to attract top performers will continue exploring trends to create workplaces with a strong purpose and the ability to maintain lifestyles with work-life well-being.</p>

<p>Leaders will also continue to focus on delivering DEI initiatives, upskilling, and reskilling opportunities while leveraging TXP platforms and AI data recruiting best practices. They will also maintain relationships with former top-performing employees through alumni networks, practice salary transparency and continue finding ways to provide workers with remote and hybrid work options. While the current job market may be facing uncertainty, there are still plenty of opportunities for insightful organizational leaders to attract top talent and create a thriving and dynamic workplace.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jenn Lackey</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hiring trends for 2023 include company leaders continuing to look for ways to attract top talent. Smart leaders are focused on innovative ways to provide their employees with well-being, a strong sense of purpose, and opportunities for growth and development to allow more options for maintaining work-life balance. DEI initiatives, upskilling and reskilling programs, cutting-edge technologies like talent experience platforms (TXP) are becoming increasingly important in the modern workplace, along with AI-powered data recruiting best practices. These tools allow leaders to recruit A-list talent and monitor employee engagement and performance. Companies are also keeping in touch with former top-performing employees through alumni networks, practicing salary transparency, and providing flexible work arrangements, such as remote and hybrid work options. While the current job market may be facing uncertainty, insightful organizational leaders still have plenty of opportunities to attract top talent and create a thriving and dynamic workplace. By focusing on delivering DEI initiatives, upskilling and reskilling opportunities, and leveraging cutting-edge technologies, leaders can help their companies stay ahead of the curve and continue to thrive in the years to come.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-edmond-dantes-4342496.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-edmond-dantes-4342496.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">6 Tips for How to Cure Imposter Syndrome as a CTO</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/01/23/6-tips-for-how-to-cure-imposter-syndrome-as-a-cto/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="6 Tips for How to Cure Imposter Syndrome as a CTO" /><published>2023-01-23T18:42:39+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-23T18:42:39+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/01/23/6-tips-for-how-to-cure-imposter-syndrome-as-a-cto</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/01/23/6-tips-for-how-to-cure-imposter-syndrome-as-a-cto/"><![CDATA[<p>Ever felt like your success was simply fooling people into thinking you were good at your job? If the answer is yes, you may suffer from imposter syndrome, especially if you’re a full-time executive or fractional executive. However, you’re not alone. It’s <a href="https://so06.tci-thaijo.org/index.php/IJBS/article/view/521">estimated that 70%</a> of all people with imposter syndrome are in high-powered positions, and Chief Technology Officers (CTOs) are no different.</p>

<p>A CTO provides technological vision, leadership, and expertise to develop technical teams and build strategic roadmaps to guide the development of an organization’s products and services. A <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/05/02/the-ultimate-guide-to-fractional-ctos/">fractional Chief Technology Officer</a> takes on the role on a part-time basis to help reduce costs and <a href="https://staffinghub.com/hiring/how-a-fractional-executive-can-move-your-company-forward/">move companies forward</a>.</p>

<p>CTOs and Fractional CTOs have the pressure of being both an expert in their field and a leader, which can be overwhelming, even to those with a strong track record of success. You might be worried about learning more about programming, project management, or product design. But there are ways to learn how to cure imposter syndrome as a CTO.</p>

<h3 id="what-is-imposter-syndrome"><strong>What is Imposter Syndrome?</strong></h3>

<p>Imposter syndrome describes the feeling that you are not qualified for your job, despite evidence to the contrary. It’s when you persistently believe you’re not good enough, and eventually, you will be exposed as a fraud.</p>

<p>With the expectation to know various technical skills and carry leadership responsibilities, you may need more time to fulfill both roles effectively. Regardless of your achievements, self-doubt and fear can derail your efforts to accomplish positive outcomes. You may fear others will judge or question your qualifications from your teams, within your organization, or field.</p>

<h2 id="how-can-imposter-syndrome-affect-a-cto"><strong>How Can Imposter Syndrome Affect a CTO?</strong></h2>

<p>Imposter syndrome can create a ruminating false narrative that your efforts will end in adverse outcomes, especially when you’re starting as a CTO or fractional CTO. If you’re new to the role or looking to gain more traction in your field, imposter syndrome can create the need to overwork yourself or your teams to meet unrealistic high standards that you’ve put in place to compensate for feelings of inadequacy.</p>

<p>It can lead to burnout, low job performance, and job dissatisfaction. As a leader, it can affect the day-to-day operations of your teams if you saddle them with too much work. If you and your teams are overloaded and burnt out, symptoms related to stress can surface. Anxiety, lack of sleep, or frustration can cause people to disengage from unhappiness and decrease performance.</p>

<p>As a leader, this is the last scenario you want. Part of your role is to set up your teams for success. When your <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/08/05/happy/">workforce is happy, they’ll perform at their best</a> and deliver high-achieving results. You want to avoid sabotaging success due to imposter syndrome.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-treat-imposter-syndrome-as-a-cto-or-fractional-cto"><strong>How to Treat Imposter Syndrome as a CTO or Fractional CTO</strong></h2>

<p>The first step toward overcoming imposter syndrome is to give yourself a break and fully understand it’s common. Here are six ways to toss those negative feelings out the window and set you on the path toward preserving the road to success:</p>

<h3 id="1-maintain-a-growth-mindset"><strong>1. Maintain a growth mindset</strong></h3>

<p>A growth mindset is about focusing on ways to get better and overcome “Impostor syndrome: ‘I don’t know what I’m doing. It’s only a matter of time until everyone finds out.’ Growth mindset: ‘I don’t know what I’m doing yet. It’s only a matter of time until I figure it out.’ The highest form of self-confidence is believing in your ability to learn,” says Organizational Psychologist and <em>Work Life</em> podcast host Adam Grant.</p>

<h3 id="2-look-for-learning-opportunities"><strong>2. Look for learning opportunities</strong></h3>

<p>When you focus on learning opportunities to strengthen your weaknesses, it redirects your focus from adverse outcomes. <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/forbesbusinesscouncil/2022/12/08/mapping-your-career-journey-with-intention/?sh=6ef56ecb7f0b">Mapping out your career intentions</a> can help ground you and provide you with a list of learning opportunities to overcome fears related to self-perceived shortcomings.</p>

<h3 id="3-focus-on-problem-solving-for-others"><strong>3. Focus on problem-solving for others</strong></h3>

<p>A CTO’s role is to support and lead teams. Focusing on solutions for others is a way to deflect attention away from yourself and relax your negative thoughts while building your confidence and expertise.</p>

<h3 id="4-create-a-network-of-support"><strong>4. Create a network of support</strong></h3>

<p><a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/07/25/8-tips-for-networking-as-a-chief-technology-officer/">Create connections</a> with people that can help you in times of need. Whether you’re a full-time or fractional leader, you want to develop a vast network of powerful individual resources to help you solve problems and provide resources to your teams to achieve your goals and initiatives.</p>

<h3 id="5-make-connections-with-problem-solving-allies"><strong>5. Make connections with problem-solving allies</strong></h3>

<p>You want to build resources and create partners with problem-solving experts to support and drive your initiatives within your client organization. This can help ensure successful outcomes for your projects that will subdue the negative chatter in your mind from imposter syndrome.</p>

<h3 id="6-delegate-your-weakness-to-others"><strong>6. Delegate your weakness to others</strong></h3>

<p>Finding ways to delegate your weaknesses to others possessing the skill sets you lack is a strategy for positive outcomes. It allows you to leverage your strengths, which boosts your self-confidence and provides new growth opportunities among teams and yourself to learn.</p>

<h2 id="can-work-as-a-fractional-cto-help-with-imposter-syndrome"><strong>Can Work as a Fractional CTO Help with Imposter Syndrome?</strong></h2>

<p>For those struggling with imposter syndrome, becoming a CTO can be daunting. However, fractional CTO work is a great way to encounter a variety of problem-solving and growth opportunities to hone your expertise toward becoming a full-time leader.</p>

<p>CTOs are <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/01/28/should-your-business-hire-a-fractional-cto/">top contributors to the financial success</a> of companies. Organizations constantly need to manage technology changes and provide solutions to innovate and maintain growth for short and long-term needs. Companies can’t afford the role to go vacant for too long, and fractional CTOs are excellent resources for filling gaps.</p>

<p>Both scenarios offer the opportunity to manage various challenges that will hone your ability to direct constant change. It’s also an excellent chance to provide much-needed value to companies. It’s also a way to leverage your existing technical expertise that landed you the job in the first place, while practicing your leadership skills part-time to build confidence.</p>

<p>Some of the benefits of fractional CTO work include:</p>

<h3 id="create-success-through-problem-solving"><strong>Create success through problem-solving</strong></h3>

<p>Working as a fractional CTO allows you to tackle the issues that will inevitably arise in organizations going through changes at a reduced cost. The problems you solve will help reduce your imposter syndrome and provide you with confidence-building success stories.</p>

<h3 id="apply-existing-skills-in-new-ways"><strong>Apply existing skills in new ways</strong></h3>

<p>You can gain experience by putting your existing skills to work in new scenarios. For example, if you want to expand your expertise and knowledge to a new industry, fractional CTO work is an excellent way to make a change. It allows you to apply expanded assurance to your existing skills in areas where imposter syndrome can appear.</p>

<h3 id="practice-leadership-skills"><strong>Practice leadership skills</strong></h3>

<p>Leading and guiding teams through change requires a firm set of calm, confident, soft skills where the challenges can be ambiguous, which is a situation ripe for imposter syndrome. Particularly if you feel like you have the technical know-how but lack leadership experience, fractional CTO work is an excellent way to build relationships. You want to work with people who can offer support and mentorship as you hone your leadership soft skills and move your career forward.</p>

<p><strong>How Do You Know if Fractional CTO Work is Right for You?</strong></p>

<p>Suppose you’re looking to expand or hone your skillsets to challenge your imposter syndrome tendencies while creating greater flexibility and autonomy in your career. In that case, <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/10/18/how-to-get-hired-as-a-fractional-executive/">fractional CTO work</a> might be a good fit for you. To decide whether or not fractional CTO work is right for you, the following is a short list of primary skills required to assess your abilities for the role:</p>

<h3 id="1-you-know-what-it-takes-to-get-things-done"><strong>1. You know what it takes to get things done</strong></h3>

<p>If you’re an experienced developer, architect, or manager, you already have the skillset and a pretty good idea of what it takes to get the job done. You’ve worked on teams before and know how much effort is required to deliver high-quality products and services.</p>

<h3 id="2-youre-a-good-communicator"><strong>2. You’re a good communicator</strong></h3>

<p>You must communicate clearly with developers, designers, and project managers to effectively accomplish project milestones and goals. So if this isn’t something that comes naturally to you, it may take some time and practice before you can do so effectively as a fractional CTO. To practice, focus on expanding your network to hone your communication skills, and look for small-scale projects you can lead.</p>

<h3 id="3-you-have-experience-leading-or-managing-teams"><strong>3. You have experience leading or managing teams</strong></h3>

<p>If you have led technical teams and managed engineers, you can take your skill set to the next level as a fractional CTO. Fractional CTOs are c-level executives who can lead and guide teams to success, which requires the soft skills to manage people effectively. In addition to having technical know-how to perform or understand specific tasks, successful fractional leaders have the professional network and outreach to help hire the appropriate resources to fulfill the skills gaps within teams when necessary.</p>

<h3 id="4-you-have-experience-working-remotely"><strong>4. You have experience working remotely</strong></h3>

<p>Working as a fractional CTO requires frequent communication with remote colleagues spread out worldwide, sometimes in different time zones. As such, it’s essential that your team members feel comfortable communicating with each other via Slack or another chat app without feeling like they need to be present in person at all times.</p>

<p>If you possess all of the above skill sets, exploring fractional CTO work is likely a good fit for you. Otherwise, it’s worth expanding your network and exploring small-scale project opportunities to build the skills you need and help quiet your imposter syndrome.</p>

<p>Remember, imposter syndrome doesn’t have to overpower you. If you’re starting your journey as a CTO or looking to break into the role in a fractional capacity, it’s a familiar feeling among high-achieving tech professionals. You can leverage it as fuel to grow your network and find the resources to develop your skills, particularly if you maintain a growth mindset with the willingness to learn.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jenn Lackey</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Imposter syndrome can create a ruminating false narrative that your efforts will end in adverse outcomes, especially when you’re starting as a CTO or fractional CTO. As a leader, this is the last scenario you want. Part of your role is to set up your teams for success. Here are six ways to toss those negative feelings out the window and set you on the path toward preserving the road to success.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/medium-shot-smiley-programmer-indoors.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/medium-shot-smiley-programmer-indoors.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Navigating Your Career Journey with Intention</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/01/13/navigating-your-career-journey-with-intention/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Navigating Your Career Journey with Intention" /><published>2023-01-13T23:53:59+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-13T23:53:59+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/01/13/navigating-your-career-journey-with-intention</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2023/01/13/navigating-your-career-journey-with-intention/"><![CDATA[<p>You spend one-third of your lifetime working. How can you navigate what you want your work to mean, and how can you contribute to meaningful employment with purpose? It takes intention.</p>

<p>When you use intention to guide your actions, rather than relying on chance, it sets the stage for greater success and happiness along your career journey.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-the-career-journey"><strong>What is the Career Journey</strong></h2>

<p>The career journey is a series of jobs and life experiences that leads you to your long-term career goals. It’s a continual process of achieving milestones and goals; learning and growing; rediscovering what you have to offer; and contributing to the greater good. Whether you’re at the start or in the middle of your career, your career journey will continue to unfold throughout your life.</p>

<p>What if you could create a personal roadmap that shows how you plan to get from where you are now to where you want to be in the future? Learning to map your career journey opens possibilities to evaluate what is important to you, assess how your career contributes to your happiness, and pivot when life throws you a curveball.</p>

<p>Even if you’ve never taken the time to map your career journey formally, it’s never too late to evaluate your current situation and consider if you’re happy continuing in that direction. Your insights will guide you to make necessary changes, discover new things about yourself, take the time to enjoy and celebrate your accomplishments, and think about what you want to do next.</p>

<p>Your career map documents the steps you want to take in your journey, and how your actions support your goals in a chosen timeline. Mapping your journey encourages regular reflection check-ins with yourself and your career intentions. You can track your progress in the milestones you achieve and the inevitable detours, roadblocks, and side roads you encounter along the way. Your map keeps you on course towards a meaningful and satisfying work life.</p>

<h2 id="identifying-your-values"><strong>Identifying Your Values</strong></h2>

<p>The first step in mapping a career journey is to define your values, and this requires some deep questioning of yourself. Reflect on your life experiences and find the values that are meaningful to you.</p>

<p>It might help to start by identifying people in your life or in public that you admire, and then examining the qualities they possess that are attractive to you. When you have completed your values audit and reflection, you can test your values by asking yourself some challenging questions to determine if your values hold up.</p>

<p>For example, if you value authenticity, can you identify times when your authentic self led you to make a difficult decision. How did you feel after doing so? Do you believe you did the right thing?</p>

<p>Once you are clear on your values, you can ensure that your actions and goals are in alignment. Your core values give your life meaning, and you can use them to create a compass for your life. This will guide you through the challenging twists and turns you will inevitably encounter, and will help you maintain the career journey you want.</p>

<p>When you take measures to intentionally live your values, chances are you’ll be motivated and inspired to express your desires and priorities.</p>

<h2 id="finding-your-true-north-in-your-career-journey"><strong>Finding Your True North in Your Career Journey</strong></h2>

<p>Metaphorically speaking, your true north is your guiding star or a galaxy of possibilities that aligns with your values. Ultimately, it’s how you’d like to contribute to the greater whole and where you’d like to make a difference to keep you engaged, growing, and sustainably happy while learning.</p>

<p>Your true north sets the stage for your priorities and goals throughout your career, regardless of circumstance. Circumstances are tricky because they often represent what you can’t fully control. You can choose to see your circumstances as challenges that derail you or as opportunities that steer the direction of your priorities. Events you don’t see coming can either create feelings of burden or of potential achievement. Regardless of circumstances, situations you can’t control can be challenging.</p>

<p>Understanding and formulating a relationship with your values defines your true north, and allows you to make optimal choices for your priorities because it feels right even when your options are difficult or painful to make based on circumstances.</p>

<p>Your true north keeps you going in the direction of your values and intentions no matter what happens throughout your career journey.</p>

<h3 id="conducting-a-skills-inventory"><strong>Conducting a Skills Inventory</strong></h3>

<p>You now have the opportunity to define the next chapter of your career. With clarity around your true north, you can assess where you stand along your journey. You’ve already put in the time to build awareness for what you want. Now it’s time to formulate a plan for getting there by identifying strengths, blockers and dependencies. Here are some ways to get started:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Celebrate existing skills:</strong> Celebrate your current skills by recognizing achievements and positive contributions. This can be as simple as taking a moment to write down what went well each day and what you’re proud of accomplishing.</li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Identify needs:</strong> Look at the areas within your skill set that you’ll need to progress to the next milestone or goal within your journey.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Evaluate weakness:</strong> Take stock of your weaknesses by asking trusted friends or peers for honest feedback on your work performance and development opportunities.</p>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Build a backlog:</strong> Create a backlog of things you want to learn, allowing you to prioritize learning opportunities over time.</li>
  <li><strong>Prioritize and attack:</strong> Prioritize which skill gaps need addressing now by identifying which ones are holding you back from doing your best work in the future.</li>
</ul>

<p>If you need to develop new skill sets, then be intentional with how you fill in skill gaps. Set aside time and resources to learn relevant skills that align with your values and direction instead of rushing to learn something new. It’s easy for distractions to take over. There’s always a new shiny object that grabs at our focus. Keep track of what is most important right now, and focus on those first before moving on to the next priority. Be deliberate about how you spend your time and energy.</p>

<p>Learning is a lifelong process, so it’s crucial to cultivate an attitude of curiosity and openness toward learning new things. This will allow you to continue developing throughout your life and, even better, build a foundation for lifelong learning.</p>

<p>During this phase of your investigation, it’s easy for distractions to take over. There’s always a new shiny object that grabs at our focus. Keep track of what is most important right now, and focus on those first before moving on to the next priority. Be deliberate about how you spend your time and energy.</p>

<p>Remember that mastery is different for everyone, but it often starts with setting goals for what success looks like for each skill gap that needs filling. For example, if there’s a programming language or framework that you want to master, then decide what level of proficiency that means for yourself: basic knowledge or expert understanding. This can help keep you motivated along the way by showing progress toward mastery.</p>

<p>Finally, maintain your skills backlog by keeping track of what you’ve learned and the projects you’ve completed with your acquired skills.This will not only keep you on your journey, but it is immensely satisfying to review how far you have come.</p>

<p>Pause here and assess if you are ready to start mapping your career journey. Can you articulate your values and see when your decisions are aligned? Have you found your true north? Is your skills inventory complete? Now it’s time to start your map.</p>

<h2 id="tips-for-building-your-career-map"><strong>Tips for Building your Career Map</strong></h2>

<p>Creating your career map is a way to proactively identify desired opportunities that match your values and interests, rather than reacting to prospects that won’t move you towards your desired goals. When you are ready to start mapping, you can follow these steps:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The first step is to gather career resources for your ideal position, such as job descriptions, required skills, personality profiles, training, and development. You need this research to ensure that you fully understand the opportunities and challenges of your journey.</li>
  <li>Next you will set a goal for your ideal career. What skills do you need to achieve that role? For example, if you desire to be a project manager, what did you learn from your research about the skills and availability of that career? If you will need to develop more skills to achieve your goal, consider how you might build the appropriate skill set. Maybe it requires that you take a series of small promotions, or maybe you’ll require some retraining.</li>
  <li>At some point in the journey, you may recognize that it is useful to create small milestones toward your goal. Map how to advance from one point to another. It’s okay If your map is <a href="https://hbr.org/2021/10/why-you-should-build-a-career-portfolio-not-a-career-path">not linear</a>, you can map your various positions and draw connections between them. Consider seminars, higher education, and certifications that will support your career journey.</li>
</ul>

<p>Advancing in your career may seem like a monumental task. Set bite-sized objectives to strive toward more significant accomplishments and build confidence to create experiences you’re proud to share.</p>

<h2 id="measuring-your-career-progress--introspection"><strong>Measuring Your Career Progress &amp; Introspection</strong></h2>

<p>Maintaining your career map reminds you to measure your progress and set reflective points during your journey that support feelings of fulfillment, accomplishment, and happiness.</p>

<p>Measurement allows you to know the actual output of your effort. It’s wise to create deadlines, milestones, objectives, and key results to document and reflect upon them regularly so that you can examine your progress, pivot when necessary, and remain motivated.</p>

<p>Reflection time on your journey puts life’s challenges into perspective, and opens opportunities for you to consider. You can thrive by reflecting on what you value most in work and in life, and what is keeping you from being your best self. When work absorbs so much of your time and attention, you owe it to yourself to find meaning in what you do daily.</p>

<p>During times of introspection, ask yourself:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What works for you at work? It’s important to ponder and write these qualities down, so you don’t run in a repeating loop. Include how you feel about the physical environment, the people, access to opportunities, harmony between work and life, and how work aligns with your values.</li>
  <li>What makes you stand out? When you get good at something, you can leverage your value in remarkably satisfying and impactful ways.</li>
  <li>How do you relate to the world? When you are using your energy to match a work environment that isn’t a natural space for you, you are less available to perform at your highest potential.</li>
  <li>What type of impact do you want to make? You can find ways to work it into your daily life, both in and out of the workplace.</li>
</ul>

<p>Focusing with intention, taking the time to reflect on your values, and mapping your career journey lays the foundation for achieving and maintaining happiness in your life and in your career. It’s worth the effort, and your future self will thank you.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This article was originally published in <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/forbesbusinesscouncil/2022/12/08/mapping-your-career-journey-with-intention/?sh=5e438f1b7f0b">Forbes</a>.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Dori Kelner</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[No matter your current position, it's important to be intentional about developing and following a career path.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-andrea-piacquadio-789822-1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-andrea-piacquadio-789822-1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Get Hired as a Fractional Executive</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/10/18/how-to-get-hired-as-a-fractional-executive/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Get Hired as a Fractional Executive" /><published>2022-10-18T21:49:01+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-18T21:49:01+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/10/18/how-to-get-hired-as-a-fractional-executive</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/10/18/how-to-get-hired-as-a-fractional-executive/"><![CDATA[<p>Companies want to hire C-level executives to help them grow. However, with rapidly changing needs and an unpredictable environment, many companies may not be able to budget for a full-time C-level executive.</p>

<p>Fast-paced organizations or companies in transition can hire an experienced leader part-time to <a href="https://staffinghub.com/hiring/how-a-fractional-executive-can-move-your-company-forward/">move a company forward</a>. Hiring fractional executives helps corporations mitigate costs and evaluate new potential leaders.</p>

<p>A fractional executive works in a fractional capacity, helping small and large companies to offload the burden of having a c-level executive in-house full-time.</p>

<h2 id="what-are-the-types-of-fractional-executives"><strong>What Are the Types of Fractional Executives</strong>?</h2>

<p>The C-level acts as the chief executives in a company, driving their organizations to grow and leading operational changes to remain competitive. They make up an organization’s leadership suite in several different roles representing expertise. Most of us know the typical C-level executive positions available such as:</p>

<ul>
  <li>CEO (Chief Executive Officer)</li>
  <li>CFO (Chief Financial Officer)</li>
  <li>CTO (Chief Technology Officer)</li>
  <li>CIO (Chief Information office)</li>
  <li>CMO (Chief Marketing Officer)</li>
</ul>

<p>Today, a wide range of C-level titles spin off these traditional acronyms. With so many variations for the chief executive label available, CXO is now a known term with the “X” representing the collective term for C-level or C-suite executive. Sometimes roles overlap, and it’s not uncommon for executives to wear multiple hats.</p>

<p>For example, an IT executive could take on the part of a CIO or CTO, or both. CIOs typically oversee IT departments and make strategic decisions about an organization’s hardware and software associated with networking systems, work staff, and customer service needs. CTOs typically focus more on the innovation aspects of the business. They oversee a business’s existing and new technology needs to develop strategic products and services. Their goal is to help grow business while keeping an eye on maintaining and optimizing technology infrastructure.</p>

<p>But what happens when a company doesn’t quite have the budget or resources for either role? One solution is to hire <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/05/02/the-ultimate-guide-to-fractional-ctos/">fractional C-level executives</a>, such as a <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/01/21/why-hire-a-fractional-cto/">fractional CTO</a>. It’s not out of reach for a highly experienced C-level IT executive to take on a part-time role as a fractional executive to help an organization grow and optimize costs.</p>

<h2 id="what-are-the-benefits-of-fractional-work-for-a-c-level-executive"><strong>What are the Benefits of Fractional Work for a C-level Executive?</strong></h2>

<p>Executives have a lot to gain from fractional roles. While fractional executives provide companies with the opportunity to save money and optimize resources, fractional work is an opportunity to make significant impacts within organizations, maintain a variety of exciting experiences, create flexibility in their work-life, and make more money. The fractional leadership model can benefit C-level executives and companies alike. Some of the benefits include:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Make an Impact:</strong> Fractional executives can make a real difference. They have the potential to cause significant impacts in shorter periods. This is because day-to-day management responsibilities do not bog them down. Also, they’re less likely to get caught up in politics. The part-time nature of their position provides less opportunity for internal politics to overshadow their decision-making. As a result, fractional executives tend to devote more time and energy to strategic thinking and implementation. With a greater focus on results, they have more opportunities to make meaningful strides toward company growth.</li>
  <li><strong>Gain Variety:</strong> Being a fractional executive is an ideal way for an experienced person to work on solving challenging problems with various great companies without having to commit to one company full time. Fractional executives can choose projects that pique their interests and cater to their strengths. They’re well positioned for success while learning new skills to add knowledge and experience to their repertoire.</li>
  <li><strong>Create Flexibility:</strong> Becoming a fractional executive is a viable option for achieving work-life balance. Fractional executives can take on multiple clients and make more money with greater flexibility. Fractional executives work on a per-project basis with no obligation for ongoing employment. They can choose when they want to work and how much time they want to dedicate to each client, enabling them to structure their schedules and avoid burnout.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-qualifications-do-you-need-to-be-a-fractional-executive"><strong>What Qualifications Do You Need to Be a Fractional Executive?</strong></h2>

<p>A fractional executive have similar but scaled-down sets of responsibilities compared to their full-time counterparts. Fractional executives generally have at least a bachelor’s degree, and many, if not most, have master’s degrees.</p>

<p>If you’re interested in becoming a fractional executive, you must show leadership experience in managing groups of people to implement change. It’s also necessary to offer the ability to scale resources, harness innovation, and effectively manage relationships with key stakeholders. In addition to a successful track record, the following skills can help you stand out from the crowd:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Strategic thinking:</strong> C-level fractional executives deeply understand their industries and organizations’ challenges and opportunities to make strategic decisions. Your ability as a fractional executives will be judged by how well you can take charge during change and uncertainty.</li>
  <li><strong>Team management:</strong> Fractional executives must work with teams on different levels of an organization, from the sales teams that report directly to you or marketing teams that register through your department head to executives who report directly to your boss’s boss or above. Your ability to communicate effectively with people at all levels is essential for success in the job.</li>
  <li><strong>Superior communication skills:</strong> Some <a href="https://hbr.org/2022/07/the-c-suite-skills-that-matter-most">essential skills</a> fractional C-suite executives must possess are the soft skills required to manage people effectively, including exceptional communication skills. Fractional executives must have the ability to communicate with a wide range of stakeholders from different backgrounds and industries. They need to be able to act as an intermediary between various departments within an organization and between organizations.</li>
  <li><strong>High emotional intelligence:</strong> Fractional executives must also possess high emotional intelligence and understand other people’s emotions. This includes understanding their emotions to respond accordingly without letting them get in the way of making rational decisions or supporting others.</li>
  <li><strong>Dedication:</strong> While the position is part-time, fractional executives must be willing to show they’re 100% dedicated to the outcomes of the results they’re trying to achieve. Ultimately, fractional executives want their clients to feel like they’re receiving full-time attention.</li>
  <li><strong>Laser-sharp scope management:</strong> Fractional executives must be able to manage scope firmly. They need to be comfortable with handling the duality of conflicting priorities, which requires the ability to make confident decisions, delegate projects, and create boundaries.</li>
</ul>

<p>If you feel like you have the right skills, experience, and credentials to become a fractional executive, then it’s a worthy option to explore, but fractional executive work isn’t for everyone.</p>

<h2 id="how-do-you-know-if-fractional-executive-work-is-right-for-you"><strong>How Do You Know if Fractional Executive Work is Right for You?</strong></h2>

<p>If you’re considering a fractional executive role and want to leverage your extensive experience to create greater flexibility and autonomy in your career, asking yourself the following questions can help determine whether fractional executive work is the right path.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Are you drawn to challenging business growth opportunities?</li>
  <li>Do you like variety and have an entrepreneurial spirit?</li>
  <li>Are you comfortable with creating direction and leading through ambiguity?</li>
  <li>Do you have expertise in a particular area that would lend itself well to this work?</li>
  <li>Do you have any barriers that could prevent you from fractional work?</li>
  <li>What are your motivations behind exploring fractional work?</li>
</ul>

<p>While these are important questions to consider when assessing the viability of pursuing fractional executive work, don’t allow yourself to be dissuaded if you find that you don’t possess all the skills or traits to do the work. The need and options for fractional executives are growing, and taking on small pilot projects is another way you can explore whether or not fractional work is the path for you.</p>

<p>However, suppose you’re an experienced C-level executive with a proven successful track record and like variety in your career. If you want to make an impact, earn more money, and have the freedom to structure your schedule, then becoming a fractional executive is likely an excellent choice.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jenn Lackey</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Companies want to hire C-level executives to help them grow. However, with rapidly changing needs and an unpredictable environment, many companies may not be able to budget for a full-time C-level executive. Here's our list on how to get hired as a fractional executive.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-andrea-piacquadio-3760371.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-andrea-piacquadio-3760371.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Fractional Screening is a Great Side-Hustle for Developers</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/09/29/why-fractional-screening-is-a-great-side-hustle-for-developers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Fractional Screening is a Great Side-Hustle for Developers" /><published>2022-09-29T21:46:51+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-29T21:46:51+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/09/29/why-fractional-screening-is-a-great-side-hustle-for-developers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/09/29/why-fractional-screening-is-a-great-side-hustle-for-developers/"><![CDATA[<p>Fractional screening is a great side hustle for web engineers with skills, experience, and some free time in their schedules. Screeners can earn additional income while using their skills to match open roles with qualified developers among their colleagues. Hiring organizations also benefit from this arrangement because they can evaluate a larger pool of potential candidates by leveraging fractional screeners to help manage their recruiting efforts and resources.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-fractional-screening"><strong>What is Fractional Screening?</strong></h2>

<p>The traditional recruitment process is a time-consuming and expensive undertaking. It requires a lot of human resources to manage the administration process for interviewing candidates and filtering out those who are not qualified despite the advances with AI sourcing tools. This is especially true for technical positions, where there are often hundreds of applicants.</p>

<p>Fractional screening is a recruitment outsourcing option that leverages professional developers with a niche or advanced technical knowledge to tackle the vetting and prequalifying filtration step during the candidate assessment process.</p>

<p>Fractional screeners are highly skilled professional developers who can provide technical interviewer services that can accurately evaluate candidates’ skills and abilities based on their experience in a particular technology, language, or platform.</p>

<p>When hiring managers fold fractional screening into their wheelhouse of technical screening tools it gives them access to many qualified candidates at a fraction of what it would typically cost to vet technical candidates internally. Without losing control over their organization’s recruiting process or sacrificing quality assurance, it alleviates the burden of screening and evaluating candidates.</p>

<h2 id="why-should-i-find-a-fractional-screening-gig"><strong>Why Should I Find a Fractional Screening Gig?</strong></h2>

<p>If you’re an experienced developer, this is an excellent way to earn extra income for <strong>paid interviews</strong> while providing your skills and expertise to companies that need them. If you haven’t considered fractional screening as an opportunity in the past, consider the numerous benefits a fractional screening gig has to offer.</p>

<h3 id="financial-stability"><strong>Financial Stability</strong></h3>

<p>As a fractional worker, you can combine multiple streams of income. This means that you can earn money whenever and wherever you want. You’ll be able to find work as needed and take on projects when you have time.</p>

<h3 id="flexibility"><strong>Flexibility</strong></h3>

<p>Fractional workers have more control over their schedules. You set your hours and work on your schedule. You can choose which projects you want to work on, thus giving you more control over how much money you earn each month. This is especially important if you have other responsibilities outside of work, such as caring for children or elderly family members.</p>

<p>It’s particularly appealing if you want to work part-time while continuing your full-time, attending school full-time or part-time, or taking the time to pursue personal goals.</p>

<h3 id="control"><strong>Control</strong></h3>

<p>As a fractional worker you’ll have the ability to choose how much or how little you want to work. You can set your schedule so that it fits into your life. You can even take breaks during the week if necessary. You’ll also have the freedom to choose the types of assignments most appealing.. You’ll have access to thousands of jobs and can apply for whatever projects interest you most. The pay is often more competitive than full-time positions, so even if the hours don’t match up perfectly with your schedule, it’s still worth considering as an alternative to a full-time job. As a fractional screener, you’ll be able to pick the jobs you want to do and the companies you want to engage for business, allowing control and freedom to manage your schedule.</p>

<h3 id="work-from-anywhere"><strong>Work from Anywhere</strong></h3>

<p>As the remote-hybrid paradigm takes hold, working from anywhere has become more important. This is simply good business practice because several studies have shown a large portion of the workforce claim that remote work allows them to be more productive. For example, 77% of those who work remotely at least a few times per month show increased productivity, with 30% doing more work in less time and 24% doing more in the same period, <a href="https://www.shrm.org/resourcesandtools/hr-topics/technology/pages/teleworkers-more-productive-even-when-sick.aspx">according to a survey by ConnectSolutions</a>.</p>

<p>Working from anywhere allows you to work with greater concentration and less distraction. Avoiding commutes and office distractions enable people to get more work done in less time, ultimately <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/bryanrobinson/2022/05/05/remote-work-increases-employee-happiness-by-20-new-study-finds/?sh=5b3a8c9c3183">providing greater happiness.</a> Fractional screening opportunities are usually fully remote, so you can work when and where it’s most convenient for you.</p>

<h3 id="autonomy"><strong>Autonomy</strong></h3>

<p>There are many benefits to a fractional screening gig, such as autonomy. Fractional screeners can “be their own boss,” at least to some degree. With autonomy, you have the freedom to work in a way that suits you best.</p>

<p>While fractional workers will need to take the time to understand their clients’ processes and business needs to set themselves up for success. By establishing relationships with stakeholders and understanding client processes, fractional screeners will have the freedom to work independently on their terms.</p>

<h3 id="helping-businesses"><strong>Helping Businesses</strong></h3>

<p>Despite the technology advancements associated with hiring technical professionals, IT managers still struggle to keep up with the hiring demands for software engineers, developers, and technology architects. As a result, technical debt builds for IT teams, and fractional screening can help.</p>

<p>Fractional screeners add bandwidth to a business’ screening and hiring process, allowing companies to <a href="https://esteemed.io/">scale their development teams with on-demand talent</a>. They ensure that only qualified applicants are submitted for open roles, which ultimately supports the <strong>technical assessment process</strong> saving the growing organization valuable time and money with streamlined hiring processes and boosted scalability.</p>

<h3 id="helping-talent"><strong>Helping Talent</strong></h3>

<p>Fractional screeners have the experience and deep knowledge to match each applicant with the best roles they can handle, to ensure the right candidates fulfill appropriate roles, ensuring success for both developers and employers. While going through the <strong>technical screening interview</strong> process can be intimidating for growing software developers, fractional screeners help talent expand and grow their skill sets, giving constructive feedback on how they can improve and strengthen their skills while practicing interviewing.</p>

<h2 id="how-can-i-get-started-with-fractional-screening-jobs">How Can I Get Started with Fractional Screening Jobs?</h2>

<p>It’s not difficult to get <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/08/24/the-beginner-s-guide-to-screening-and-evaluating-tech-candidates/">started with fractional screening</a> as a <strong>technical interviewer</strong> to evaluate tech candidates. Suppose you know how to code well enough to assess candidates’ technical ability. In that case, you’re already on your way to learning <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/03/07/technical-screening-in-2022-15-methods-for-assessing-senior-and-junior-developers/">screening methods for determining</a> developers to fulfill a consistent and steady demand for top tech talent.</p>

<p>Overall the benefits of a fractional screening gig as a side hustle are abundant. Fractional screening gigs can provide:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Additional financial stability,</li>
  <li>Control over how much you work</li>
  <li>Ability to work from anywhere</li>
  <li>Autonomy to be your own boss</li>
  <li>The option to work from anywhere</li>
</ul>

<p>Ultimately, you’ll help businesses and talent thrive while earning a few extra dollars, and everybody wins. <a href="https://mailchi.mp/aaf01eaf0a4c/esteemed-screening-sign-up-page">Get started with us today!</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Matt Obert</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fractional screening is a great side hustle for web engineers with skills, experience, and some free time in their schedules. Screeners can earn additional income while using their skills to match open roles with qualified developers among their colleagues. Hiring organizations also benefit from this arrangement because they can evaluate a larger pool of potential candidates by leveraging fractional screeners to help manage their recruiting efforts and resources.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/fractionalscreeninghero.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/fractionalscreeninghero.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How Coworking Spaces Have Helped the Shift toward Remote Hybrid Work</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/09/12/how-coworking-spaces-have-helped-the-shift-toward-remote-hybrid-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Coworking Spaces Have Helped the Shift toward Remote Hybrid Work" /><published>2022-09-12T18:16:43+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-12T18:16:43+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/09/12/how-coworking-spaces-have-helped-the-shift-toward-remote-hybrid-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/09/12/how-coworking-spaces-have-helped-the-shift-toward-remote-hybrid-work/"><![CDATA[<p>The hybrid model has now taken hold. Companies have become aware of the benefits of remote and office-based work. Statistics show, however, that employees want a flexible remote hybrid model.</p>

<p>A recent report from<a href="https://venturebeat.com/business/report-85-of-employees-want-a-hybrid-work-model/"> Condeco</a> found that 85% of their 1500 US-based workers desire remote and hybrid work options. Employees increasingly want employers to allow them to function from anywhere and anytime, across whatever time zones. As a result,<a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/06/29/8-ways-2022-is-impacting-hiring/"> companies should aim to meet their employees’ desires</a> for remote hybrid work.</p>

<p>While many companies during the pandemic were able to transition to remote hybrid work quickly, an<a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/01/26/8-ways-2020-impacted-workplaces-and-hiring/"> unprecedented shift in traditional workplaces</a> and the<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/10/business/remote-work-office-life.html"> way we work</a> is taking shape.</p>

<h3 id="what-is-remote-hybrid-work"><strong>What Is Remote Hybrid Work?</strong></h3>

<p>Remote Hybrid work is a combination of working in the office and working remotely. Working remotely can include operating from home, or working for a company without a headquarters. In solely remote companies, employees work from wherever they want, including outside of their home country.</p>

<p>Working remotely can also include shared workplaces or coworking spaces, like coffee shops, lounges, or workspace rentals. These spaces also offer shared <a href="https://www.outsite.co/">housing and hoteling options</a> for individual remote workers, or for <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/08/18/remote-team-retreats-8-reasons-why-your-company-needs-one/">teams to gather in a chosen central destination.</a></p>

<p>Hybrid models require flexibility to accommodate working across time zones while balancing others’ needs. Remote hybrid work combines both models. However, remote hybrid work is more than WFH on MWF and commuting into the office on Tuesdays and Thursdays. It’s an elastic combination of employees working together, based on location and schedules.</p>

<p>With remote hybrid models, as long as teams can coordinate with each other to complete deliverables, finish projects, and accomplish milestones to complete company objectives, employees can choose where and when they want to work.</p>

<h3 id="remote-coworking-increases-revenue"><strong>Remote Coworking Increases Revenue</strong></h3>

<p>For companies adopting a remote hybrid model, remote coworking spaces offer many benefits to companies looking for ways to reduce real estate costs, increase well-being and productivity. It’s also a way for organizations to become central coworking hubs to bring their remote hybrid employees together in<a href="https://www.outsite.co/locations/sagres"> exciting places</a> for <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/08/18/remote-team-retreats-8-reasons-why-your-company-needs-one/">innovation and collaboration</a>.</p>

<p>Providing remote coworking spaces for the workforce is one way companies can save a bundle, which brings in more revenue. Before the pandemic, coworking spaces such as <a href="https://www.deskmag.com/en/coworking-spaces/corporate-company-coworking-spaces-drivers-benefits-challenges-983">Mindspace</a> and <a href="https://www.thecannon.com/blog/why-big-corporations-are-moving-into-coworking-spaces">Office Evolution</a> touted cost savings of 20% to 40% for companies investing in shared workspaces versus traditional leased office space.</p>

<p><a href="https://globalworkplaceanalytics.com/resources/costs-benefits#toggle-id-5">Global Workplace Analytics</a> has done extensive research on the benefits of remote and flexible work, which includes insights to the significant real estate savings organizations can save by ditching their long-term lease investments. For example their aggregated research showed:</p>

<ul>
  <li>IBM slashed real estate costs by $50 million</li>
  <li>Average real estate savings with full-time telework is $10,000/employee/year</li>
  <li>Sun Microsystems saves $68 million a year in real estate costs</li>
</ul>

<p>Now, coworking spaces are back in demand. Recent reports from the <a href="https://www.thebusinessresearchcompany.com/report/coworking-space-global-market-report">Business Research Company</a> expects the global coworking space market to reach $30 billion in 2026 from $13 billion in 2021.</p>

<h3 id="flexible-workspaces-create-a-productive-culture"><strong>Flexible Workspaces Create a Productive Culture</strong></h3>

<p>Over the past three years, companies have focused even more on providing flexible workspaces that cater to a remote hybrid workforce. The benefits? Enhanced company culture, in-person connection, and promoted well-being among employees.</p>

<p>Atlassian and Salesforce are leading the trend right now. For example, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/anniedeanzaitzeff_atlassian-teamanywhere-activity-6958096860620189697-E-qn/?utm_source=linkedin_share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop_web">Atlassian</a> recently launched its <em>Team Anywhere</em> office from Austin. And, <a href="https://www.salesforce.com/news/stories/introducing-trailblazer-ranch/">Salesforce</a> created Trail Blazer Ranch in the Santa Cruz Mountains.</p>

<p>In addition to cost savings, organizations providing coworking spaces can benefit from productivity gains. Companies offering subsidized coworking memberships to their employees show they take their workforce needs seriously.</p>

<p>Coworking spaces can help overcome the challenges associated with remote hybrid work significantly. Many employees experience isolation, lack of structure, and blurred boundaries between personal and work time while working from home. When employers offer coworking options, workers can experience increased well-being and quality of life, resulting in greater productivity.</p>

<h3 id="remote-hybrid-workspaces-provide-community"><strong>Remote Hybrid Workspaces Provide Community</strong></h3>

<p>Even if your workforce has adapted well toward creating private workspaces within their homes, it’s still easy to fall out of balance. The personal needs of household members or the to-do list to manage home life can easily disrupt a workday.</p>

<p>A surefire way to tackle the issues associated with remote hybrid work is for companies to provide the option of a remote shared workspaces. A remote shared workspace can provide employees with the structure and boundaries needed to create more focus, mitigate personal distractions and overcome feelings of isolation.</p>

<p>A shared workspace can immediately reduce the problem of loneliness related to isolation, particularly in spaces with other remote workers. Long before the pandemic coworking hubs became widely popular among freelancers and a growing number corporate teleworkers. The benefits are hard to deny. The following<a href="https://hbr.org/2017/12/coworking-is-not-about-workspace-its-about-feeling-less-lonely"> Harvard Business Review</a> research study surveying members of co-working spaces show:</p>

<ul>
  <li>79% said co-working expanded their social networks</li>
  <li>83% reported they are less lonely since joining a co-working space</li>
  <li>89% reported they are happier since joining a co-working space</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="shared-workspaces-offer-focus"><strong>Shared Workspaces Offer Focus</strong></h3>

<p>In addition to reducing feelings of isolation, becoming a member of a shared workspace can provide the structure needed to focus on work. Shared working environments are excellent sources for technology hubs providing high-speed internet access and plenty of ports to keep your devices charged. Members of co-working hubs surveyed in the Harvard Business Review study reported fewer distractions than working from home or in a coffee shop.</p>

<p>Co-working spaces provide the feeling of working from the office and give workers the structure and the boundaries they need to focus and create a better work-life balance. Shared work environments can provide stronger boundaries between work and home life with the following:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A focused workplace outside of home to mitigate distractions</li>
  <li>A reason to dress for success and conduct video calls in a professional manner</li>
  <li>An ability to create boundaries for work hours that won’t impede personal time</li>
</ul>

<p>When workers can concentrate better, they can function more efficiently and proactively. Shared workspaces and options present remote workers the choice of their preferred  work environments. When companies provide various workspace options, employees have the chance to perform at their best.</p>

<p>Coworking spaces give companies and their staff more choices in their work-life. It shows employers are willing to take action. It also leverages an opportunity to save money. Ultimately, shared workspaces create win-win scenarios for employers and employees shifting to the remote hybrid model.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jenn Lackey</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here’s a definition of the remote hybrid work model, hybrid work place, and how coworking spaces save companies money, support productivity, and generate revenue.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-helena-lopes-1015568.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-helena-lopes-1015568.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Remote Team Retreats: 8 Reasons Why Your Company Needs One</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/08/18/remote-team-retreats-8-reasons-why-your-company-needs-one/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Remote Team Retreats: 8 Reasons Why Your Company Needs One" /><published>2022-08-18T21:17:48+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-18T21:17:48+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/08/18/remote-team-retreats-8-reasons-why-your-company-needs-one</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/08/18/remote-team-retreats-8-reasons-why-your-company-needs-one/"><![CDATA[<p>If you work in a distributed workforce or lead teams among remote and hybrid workforce models, remote team retreats are a highly effective way for your organization to collaborate. Not only can offsite retreats help build company culture and shared values, but they’re also essential for increasing productivity, learning development, strategizing company objectives, and sparking innovation.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-a-remote-team-retreat"><strong>What is a Remote Team Retreat?</strong></h2>

<p>A remote team retreat is an opportunity for remote organizations to bring employees together in person. It’s a chance to get away from the day-to-day routine and focus on what matters most – connection among teams and company priorities. With all the daily distractions and demands at your home office or hybrid workplace, it can be hard to find the time to reflect on your work goals.</p>

<p>Sometimes it’s challenging to take a step back and simply focus on human interaction with your colleagues without a work agenda. A remote work retreat allows you to hit the reset button, learn something new, foster more profound insights, and create stronger connections with your colleagues.</p>

<h2 id="why-host-a-remote-team-retreat"><strong>Why Host a Remote Team Retreat?</strong></h2>

<p>With more companies embracing hybrid and remote work models, many organizations have to shift their best practices of team building and company culture. Some companies are choosing to close their offices permanently and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/02/25/business/offsite-corporate-retreats.html">invest in offsite remote team retreats</a>.</p>

<p>Hosting a <strong>team offsite</strong> is a powerful remote team building and company camaraderie opportunity. It brings teams together in an informal setting that promotes collaboration and fun while allowing staff to connect with each other on a more personal level. They are also an excellent way to foster relationships between coworkers who may not get the chance to interact with each other on a daily basis.</p>

<p>If you’re looking for ways to bring your teams and organization together to boost your company’s performance and solidify a vision, here are 8 reasons why your company needs a remote team retreat.</p>

<h3 id="1-build-company-culture"><strong>1. Build Company Culture</strong></h3>

<p>Leaders need to keep their workforce updated with the company vision and objectives to maintain a strong culture and keep people focused on the same goals, which creates better outcomes for success.</p>

<p>When managing a remote team or hybrid organization, building culture and creating a collective employee experience with a shared vision can be challenging. When you manage to get everyone in the same place, keeping everyone engaged and focused on company goals can be tricky. Remote team retreats are a great way to address both issues.</p>

<p>When you bring employees together offsite away from their home offices or local workspaces, particularly in an <a href="https://www.outsite.co/?utm_campaign=Partner&amp;utm_source=Esteemed">inspiring location</a> with team building and learning activities, everyone has the opportunity to be focused and engaged. Fostering a shared vision while getting to know each other better during a group experience helps build company culture.</p>

<h3 id="2-promote-and-provide-learning-development"><strong>2. Promote and Provide Learning Development</strong></h3>

<p>Offsite company retreats also provide a unique opportunity for employees to develop and learn as individuals and in groups. For example, providing a session on time management can help your teams manage themselves better for personal and organizational success.</p>

<p>Providing learning opportunities that enable your teams to explore personal, group, and organizational goals will help everyone leave on the same page. For instance, suppose leaders want to be more strategic with incorporating their company’s mission or vision into specific team objectives and operational plans. A remote work retreat can give leaders the chance to educate their teams with a better understanding of their company, and explore new approaches of how groups must function to meet company milestones.</p>

<p>A team offsite also can help your teams <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/02/6-soft-skills-every-developer-needs-to-get-hired/">practice skills</a> and develop a functional understanding of their personal leadership abilities. They enable your teams to explore how the dynamics of their groups flesh out by providing experiences that allow your teams to explore each other’s personal differences in a safe and controlled atmosphere.</p>

<h3 id="3-strategize"><strong>3. Strategize</strong></h3>

<p>A remote team retreat is an opportunity to discuss your strategy for the next six months or year and brainstorm strategies on how to achieve collective goals cross-functionally. It allows leaders to align everyone on the same page and get feedback on what they need from their managers or other departments to succeed.</p>

<p>Leaders can facilitate strategic interactive planning sessions to gather buy-in for their current mission and develop transparent planning processes for their company objectives. It’s a way to collectively gather specific information and ideas from their team members and stakeholders across the organization. Strategic interactive sessions also can pave the way to uncover or resolve organizational barriers and potential team roadblocks, which can help set reasonable expectations and spark innovative ideas to solve problems.</p>

<h3 id="4-spark-innovation"><strong>4. Spark Innovation</strong></h3>

<p>Do you want to disrupt an existing market or find new ways to expand your products and services? Innovation is the key to making your organization stand out and solve problems no one else can.</p>

<p>Offsite team retreats pull people out of their traditional settings and create time and space for new ideas to emerge and thrive through collaboration in a safe place. When team members are in a safe space, they’re more likely to ask questions, admit mistakes, and share learnings.</p>

<p>Giving your teams practice to foster curiosity and feel comfortable sharing ideas without fear of judgment will help build innovative teams more likely to achieve company goals and adapt to challenges and change with greater resilience.</p>

<h3 id="5-increase-productivity"><strong>5. Increase Productivity</strong></h3>

<p>Increased productivity is one of the many benefits why team building is important. Team building for remote workers is essential to help increase motivation and promote cooperation.</p>

<p>Teams don’t bond overnight. It can take time for people to feel comfortable and build trust with one another. When you host a remote team retreat with activities and events, you provide the chance for your remote workforce to bond. Bonded teams are more productive because they’re likely to be more committed to supporting one another and reaching collective company goals.</p>

<p>Team building gives your workforce the chance to learn how their colleagues best operate and understand one another better. It improves communication and trust breaking ground for teams to work more efficiently with each other to save time and energy.</p>

<h3 id="6-attract-and-retrain-top-talent"><strong>6. Attract and Retrain Top Talent</strong></h3>

<p>In the current job market, attracting <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/11/04/how-to-find-a-talented-remote-team-for-your-startup/">talented employees</a> is still challenging. Employees that offer hybrid and remote work options, along with opportunities to mitigate burnout, foster learning and development, and provide time and space where employees can connect beyond the workplace, are desirable to top talent and younger generations.</p>

<p>Remote team retreats show employees you’re a forward-thinking company that invests in workforce development. It’s an action that shows you value your teams enough to invest in them, especially when distributed workforces have less opportunity for face-to-face interaction.</p>

<p>Beyond the standard vacation, health care, and 401K benefits, remote work retreats can be considered an additional perk to attract A-list employees. Offsite retreats in places rich in nature or culture are a fantastic way for companies to promote well-being and have fun.</p>

<p>Employees that play together stay together. Employees who connect and build stronger relationships during remote team events and learning activities often perform better, creating more employee satisfaction. Employees are less likely to look for other opportunities<a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/08/05/happy/"> if they are happy</a>.</p>

<p>Bonded employees also have greater loyalty and responsibility toward supporting each other and the company’s vision, which fuels dedication and a greater willingness to endure company challenges and changes through growth and expansion, thus <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/henrydevries/2022/02/23/how-to-increase-revenues-with-a-get-out-of-the-way-strategic-retreat/?sh=3a9a865a205d">generating more company revenue</a>.</p>

<h3 id="7-strengthen-your-team-bonds-across-borders"><strong>7. Strengthen Your Team Bonds across Borders</strong></h3>

<p>A remote team retreat gives distributed workforces the ability to interact with their coworkers face-to-face and feel like they’re a part of the same team, despite being dispersed. Teams will have a better chance of understanding how their teammates collaborate and communicate, which helps them improve their relationships with others on their teams.</p>

<p>It also can help bridge communication gaps and provide insights toward solving problems that wouldn’t occur otherwise because in-person interaction gives people the chance to understand each other’s differences and points of view with greater clarity.</p>

<h3 id="8-spread-brand-awareness"><strong>8. Spread Brand Awareness</strong></h3>

<p>A remote team retreat also can be a marketing opportunity. It’s an opportunity to invite key stakeholders, partners, or local customers and sponsor networking opportunities with your brand, allowing your team members to meet and interact with people they usually wouldn’t meet. It’s another way for companies to strengthen a company’s brand awareness and reputation in the marketplace.</p>

<p>Company retreats can help solidify connections with all the people that created success for your organization. Plus, if you host a successful remote team retreat, your employees are more likely to become brand ambassadors, promoting your organization as a great workplace.</p>

<p>In the end, <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2022/04/01/8-tips-for-hosting-a-remote-team-retreat/">hosting a successful team retreat</a> all comes down to creating a space where everyone feels comfortable. It gives leaders and their teams the chance to come together and collaborate in ways that will further encourage better productivity and growth.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jenn Lackey</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you work in a distributed workforce or lead teams among remote and hybrid workforce models, remote team retreats are a highly effective way for your organization to collaborate. Not only can offsite retreats help build company culture and shared values, but they're also essential for increasing productivity, learning development, strategizing company objectives, and sparking innovation.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/62a3558e09a1878b892a3f6e_62148e8daf41fbb439393cc3_9_opt.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/62a3558e09a1878b892a3f6e_62148e8daf41fbb439393cc3_9_opt.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>